<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Euchodia. Or, A prayer-song; being sacred poems on the history of the birth and passion of our blessed Saviour, and several other choice texts of Scripture. In two parts. / By Daniel Cudmore, Gent.</title>
            <author>Cudmore, Daniel, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 150 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81112</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1606_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1498_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208455</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867409</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867409</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170697</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81112)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170697)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 192:E1498[2] or 203:E1606[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Euchodia. Or, A prayer-song; being sacred poems on the history of the birth and passion of our blessed Saviour, and several other choice texts of Scripture. In two parts. / By Daniel Cudmore, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Cudmore, Daniel, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for William Ley in Paul's Chain.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>With an additional title page, engraved.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copies:  E.1606[2]: "8ber [i.e. October] 22"; E.1498[2]: "March. 9. 1654"; the 5 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Passion --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Nativity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Biography --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Or, A PRAYER-SONG; BEING Sacred Poems ON THE HISTORY OF THE BIRTH and PASSION OF OUR Bleſſed SAVIOUR, And ſeveral other choice texts of SCRIPTURE.</p>
            <p>In two PARTS.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Daniel Cudmore,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>William Ley</hi> in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Chain. 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>engraved title page</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or A Prayer-Song. Being Sacred Poem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. On y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hiſtory of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> birth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> paſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Blessed Savioiur. And ſeveral other choyce texts of Scripture. by Daniel Cudmore Gent.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>And Wee are his witnſses of theſe things.</p> 
                     <bibl>Acts. 5.32.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraved panel</figDesc>
                     <q>
                        <p>Behold a Virgine &amp;</p> 
                        <bibl>Mathew. 1.23.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraved panel</figDesc>
                     <q>
                        <p>This <hi>Ieſus</hi> which is taken up into.</p> 
                        <bibl>Acts. 1.11.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraved panel</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraved panel</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraved panel</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraved panel</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraved panel</figDesc>
                     <q>
                        <p>Behold the man</p>
                        <bibl>Iohn 10.5.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>engraved panel</figDesc>
                     <q>
                        <p>Hee is not heare but is riſen</p>
                        <bibl>Mat 28.6.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </figure>
                  <p>
                     <hi>La Printed by I:C: for William Ley at Paul's Chayne. 1655.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:3"/>
            <head>To his honoured Friend <hi>HENRY WORTH</hi> Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN <hi>Italy</hi> they have a Proverb, that <hi>Paper bluſheth not:</hi> intimating thereby, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that what we are aſhamed perhaps to tender in perſon, the pale meſſenger of an <hi>Epiſtle</hi> will not bluſh to preſent. On theſe terms it is, that (having uſurp'd your Name in this Dedication, and being more happy (if in either) in my Pen then Tongue, (and ſo more obliged to the <hi>Printer</hi> then to <hi>Nature</hi>) I beg your pardon and acceptance. I am not ignorant what cenſures I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in this adventure; <hi>viz</hi> that the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation indeed is good, as being portions of Scripture; but the ſuperſtructure, <hi>wood, hay, and ſtubble,</hi> as being not ſupplied with materials from thoſe <hi>Hurams</hi> of Spirit and
<pb facs="tcp:170697:4"/>Learning; and ſo rather <hi>apples</hi> of lead, than of <hi>gold, in theſe pictures of ſilver:</hi> that what <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaid in modeſty of his Works, may be ſaid in earneſt of mine, <hi>That the Paper is more worth then the Work.</hi> Theſe Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and more than I can anticipate, much leſs prevent, have purſued me to Sanctuary under the ſhadow of your <hi>EA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GLES</hi> wing, where I doubt neither of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance nor ſafety. Not that I would make your Patronage an <hi>Aſylum</hi> for Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or your Protection a Refuge for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate Boldneſs: but that I know your Noble nature to be ever ready to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the endeavours, and to protect the ſtudies of Vertue and Honeſty; whereof as I ſhall ſtill endeavour to be a conſtant embracer, ſo of you always a true honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: in token whereof, I humbly devote my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study in</hi> Tiverton <date>
                     <hi>this <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your obliged ſervant,<hi>Daniel Cudmore.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:4"/>
            <head>To his induſtrious Friend, Mr. DANIEL CUDMORE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Dare preſume to tell the bold-fac'd Times,</l>
               <l>Divinity looks best, thus cloath'd in Rymes.</l>
               <l>Of all the Factions that have crept of late</l>
               <l>Into the bowels of our whining State,</l>
               <l>None's like the <hi>Momuſites;</hi> for ev'ry one</l>
               <l>Studies to carp, nay ſcarce lets God alone.</l>
               <l>Deſtroy'd by tongues the tow'r of <hi>Babel</hi> lies;</l>
               <l>Heav'n grant we fall not by our Hereſies.</l>
               <l>Believe me, Friend, thy Labours ſhew thou art</l>
               <l>Indu'd with Wiſdom; and thy ſerious heart</l>
               <l>Hath no outragious Faction, but each line</l>
               <l>Diſtil'd from heav'n, tells us that they are thine.</l>
               <l>Go on with courage: though Religion lie</l>
               <l>Now groaning under ſad Deformity,</l>
               <l>And at this time bears an Ecliptick ſtain,</l>
               <l>'T will end in conqueſt, and ſhine bright again.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jo. Quarles.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:5"/>
            <head>To the worthy Author.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>GOod works are their own praiſers: they that ſhow</l>
               <l>What 'tis to praiſe a work, praiſe what they know.</l>
               <l>I'll tell thee, friend, thy labor was my pain</l>
               <l>In reading; and that reading, was my gain.</l>
               <l>I did not onely reade, but underſtood</l>
               <l>What 't was I read; and therefore ſay, 'T is good.</l>
               <l>And if my erring judgement have miſtook,</l>
               <l>Let the world judge my Judgment, not thy Book.</l>
               <l>I'll therefore ſecond what I ſaid before:</l>
               <l>'Tis good, I'm ſure 'tis good; and what needs more?</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed> 
                  <hi>Ric. Harriſon,</hi> Inte. Tomp.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>To the ingenious Author, upon his Book.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TO praiſe thy work were but to work thy praiſe;</l>
               <l>'T is Vertue that thou aimſt at, &amp; not Bays:</l>
               <l>Thy Work is thy Encomium; therefore I</l>
               <l>Will ſpend no time in Prodigality</l>
               <l>Of flatt'ring praiſe: but this in ſhort I'll tell;</l>
               <l>I read, I lik'd, I prais'd: and ſo farewel.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed> 
                  <hi>Charles Hubburt,</hi> Gr. Inne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:5"/>
            <head>The Introduction.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 90.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="17">17 Prosper thou the works of our hands upon us; O proſper thou our handy-work.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>LOrd, thou without whoſe-bleſſing &amp; ſucceſs,</l>
               <l>Our Wits degenerate to Wickedneſs;</l>
               <l>Who if thou bidſt not <hi>Write,</hi> that book may die</l>
               <l>In ſhame, or prove the Author's <hi>Tragedie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who</hi> David<hi>'s tongue mad'ſt as a ready pen,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When thee he prais'd the faireſt of all men:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O make my pen as ready as his tongue,</l>
               <l>In this my <hi>Euchodie and Prayer-ſong:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Refine my Wit, to Wiſdom, in this Poem;</l>
               <l>Accept the Dedication, ſpeak the Proem.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Naaman</hi> love his proud <hi>Damaſcus</hi> ſtreams,</l>
               <l>And others hug their <hi>Heliconian</hi> dreams:</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſprings alone that flow from <hi>Sions</hi> hill</l>
               <l>Shall drench my barren brain, and moiſt my quill.</l>
               <l>But ſince all ſprings inſpire not, but befool,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs thy <hi>Angel of Betheſda's pool</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:170697:6"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deſcend and move them with his healing grace;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Unleſs thy Spirit move upon their face:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh would they now deſcend and ſo baptize</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My childiſh fancie in theſe</hi> Myſteries:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then ſhould I ſing thy Birth, as if my breſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With one of</hi> thoſe thy Angels <hi>were poſſeſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And write thy deeds, as if thou hadſt afforded</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me</hi> what th' Evangeliſts have not recorded:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So would I wail thy death, that ſome ſhould think</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy</hi> vinegar and gall <hi>my onely Ink;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My Pen ſhould be ſo tart, that it ſhould tear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And deeper pierce then did the</hi> Souldiers ſpear.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But thou who knew'ſt our weakneſs by the ſenſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of a dear-purchaſed experience,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Have pity on my</hi> Ignorance, <hi>and daign</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Some ſparks of native</hi> wiſdom <hi>here again;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That in this, men of a judicious head</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If not thy</hi> Image, <hi>may thy</hi> footſteps <hi>read.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet let not th' earth, thus by thy footſteps trod,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be proud, but ſtill remember 't is a clod;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leſt it thy praiſes curtal, and abridge</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thee of thy right, by</hi> Paper-ſacriledge.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170697:6"/>
            <head>On the Nativity of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="10">10—Behold, I bring you good tidings of great joy that ſhall be to all people.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 For unto us is born this day in the city of David a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>LEt none hence wonder that the ſouls vaſt nature</l>
               <l>Is comprehended in ſo ſmall a ſtature:</l>
               <l>That wonder's crampt, that mirrour here exploded;</l>
               <l>For in this child there is compriz'd a <hi>Godhead.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But ſtay, do not the heav'ns crouch at his feet,</l>
               <l>And beg the honour of a bearing-ſheet?</l>
               <l>Doth not the <hi>Sun</hi> deſcend on earth to ſhine</l>
               <l>And take his <hi>Palace,</hi> for a nobler Signe?</l>
               <l>Doth not the <hi>Moon,</hi> like ſome great <hi>maid of honor,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With all the <hi>troops of ſtars</hi> attending on her,</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170697:7"/>
               <l>Sue for ſome office? No, bleſt Childe, my Muſe</l>
               <l>Doth veil her crown, and humbly begs excuſe:</l>
               <l>A Quill from th' <hi>Angel's</hi> wing that ſung thy birth,</l>
               <l>Were a fit Pen to carol forth our mirth.</l>
               <l>Thou didſt deveſt thy ſelf of much more glory,</l>
               <l>That thou mightſt clothe us with intranſitory.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sun</hi>'s too weak of luſtre, it would frown</l>
               <l>Amongſt the glories of a <hi>Martyr's</hi> crown;</l>
               <l>And the dull glory of the azur'd ſtage,</l>
               <l>But a poor <hi>Pageant</hi> to their <hi>equipage.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But may I draw the veil, and not deſerve</l>
               <l>T' have one eternal on my viſive nerve?</l>
               <l>'Twas not long ſince thy <hi>fiery-pointed eye</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Did ſparkle with conſuming Majeſtie;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And is it all confin'd, compriſed all</l>
               <l>Within the circuit of this gellied ball?</l>
               <l>'Twas not long ſince <hi>thou breath'dſt in us our ſouls;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſince, <hi>thy breath did kindle burning coles:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And do we dare thy noſtrils? heark, O wonder!</l>
               <l>He cries, whom erſt I've heard to <hi>roar in thunder.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Twas not long ſince ſuch glory <hi>Moſes</hi> drew</l>
               <l>From ſee'ng thy back-parts none his face could view:</l>
               <l>And can we ſee thy face? do not, w'implore,</l>
               <l>Brandiſh deſtructive glory th'row each pore.</l>
               <l>'Twas not long ſince, at thy commanding word,</l>
               <l>The world ſprung out of nought, like <hi>Jonah</hi>'s guord;</l>
               <l>And ſince at <hi>Sinai</hi>'s mount, did <hi>Iſrael</hi> crie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let not the Lord ſpeak to us, leſt we die.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170697:7"/>
               <l>And is the <hi>mighty Counſellor</hi> ſo weak;</l>
               <l>And <hi>he that gave the tongue,</hi> can he not ſpeak?</l>
               <l>And muſt their glories all be underſtood</l>
               <l>To be wrapt up in humble fleſh and blood?</l>
               <l>A Series of wonders! which nor men</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Angels</hi> can nor comprehend nor pen:</l>
               <l>Therefore as <hi>Angels</hi> humbly veil at it</l>
               <l>Their Wiſdoms crowns, let us our crowns of Wit.</l>
               <l>That <hi>Spirit</hi> who conceiv'd thee, <hi>he</hi> can teach</l>
               <l>How to conceive a Wonder of this reach:</l>
               <l>By him my ſoul a knowledge of thy worth</l>
               <l>Brings forth as eaſie as thou wert brought forth.</l>
               <l>Hence then let's fetch our <hi>Epoche,</hi> and call</l>
               <l>This bleſſed day the birth-day of us all.</l>
               <l>What did our carnal birth boot us? this morn</l>
               <l>Redeems us who condemned were ere born.</l>
               <l>O might I now, by vertue of thy birth,</l>
               <l>Be born anew! 'twould adde to this days mirth;</l>
               <l>And th' <hi>Angels who did at thy birth rejoyce,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>At mine in ſinging would lift up their voice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bleſt Childe! that <hi>met'ſt the heaven with a ſpan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet in a ſpan art couch'd; that <hi>doſt contain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Th' earth in meaſure;</hi> Lord, yet 'tis thy pleaſure</l>
               <l>To be contained in an earthen meaſure.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The heav'n of heav'ns cannot contain thy grace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor art thou ſtraiten'd in a little place.</l>
               <l>Come then, take up my heart, and until death,</l>
               <l>O make my breſt thy bleſſed <hi>Nazareth.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:170697:8"/>
            <head>On the murther of the Innocents.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="16">16. Then Herod when he ſaw that he was mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the wiſe-men, was exceeding wroth, and ſent forth, and ſlew all the children that were in Bethlehem from two yeers old and under, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the time which he had diligently enquired of the wiſe-men.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>GOod Babes! of whom I may ſay true,</l>
               <l>For Chriſt ye did an off ring fall,</l>
               <l>And di'd for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ere <hi>Chriſt</hi> for you;</l>
               <l>Although none could his love foreſtal.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bleſt Infantry!</hi> your <hi>Sov'raign's taſters</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To him of <hi>Herod</hi>'s cup of Malice,</l>
               <l>Ere Chriſt to finiſh his diſaſters,</l>
               <l>Drank deep and free the final <hi>Chalice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bleſt Innocents!</hi> with whom the caſe thus ſtood,</l>
               <l>Firſt circumciſed, then baptiz'd in blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170697:8"/>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Sweet <hi>Saplings!</hi> who to ſpell the <hi>Branch,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fall ſubject under <hi>Herod</hi>'s rape;</l>
               <l>VVhoſe <hi>Boureauxes</hi> cut and blanch,</l>
               <l>And rob you of your juyce and ſap.</l>
               <l>You got <hi>(bleſt Cyons)</hi> by this craft;</l>
               <l>And you may bleſs curs'd <hi>Herod</hi>'s knife:</l>
               <l>Be'ng hence tranſplanted, y'are ingraft,</l>
               <l>And bourgeon on the <hi>tree of life;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where each <hi>Herodian cicatrice</hi> doth bloom</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Aaron</hi>'s <hi>rod:</hi> ſo may you bleſs your doom.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Curs'd <hi>Fox!</hi> Hell with thy brains did club,</l>
               <l>Thus needleſly to back thy claim:</l>
               <l>But could not blinde rage ſpare thy <hi>Cub?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Muſt he fall too, before thy aim?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Foxes</hi> uſe prey abroad, but thou</l>
               <l>(Although unwittingly) at home:</l>
               <l>Ambitious madneſs asks not now</l>
               <l>Whoſe't is thou prey'ſt upon, or whom.</l>
               <l>Juſt! ſince thou haſt <hi>no bowels,</hi> that thy ſon</l>
               <l>Should fall amongſt the reſt a ſlaughter'd one.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170697:9"/>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Thus <hi>Pharaoh</hi> (like our greedy
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>The Arms of</hi> Rich. 3. <hi>who ſlew his brothers children.</hi>
                  </note> Hog,</l>
               <l>Or of the kennel with this <hi>Fox</hi>)</l>
               <l>Who more ador'd <hi>Anubis dog,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then the plainneſs of <hi>Iſis ox,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Once fearing <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s increaſe,</l>
               <l>Enjoyn'd each one to drown each male,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Iſr'el</hi> groaning for releaſe,</l>
               <l>Their prayers to their <hi>God</hi> exhale;</l>
               <l>Till <hi>he</hi> deſcends, and in one fatal morn</l>
               <l>Slew each Egyptian's, and the King's firſt-born.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>But <hi>you</hi> whoſe doctrine, like the crabs,</l>
               <l>Swims backward 'gainſt the ſtream of Truth;</l>
               <l>Speak, In what <hi>Lymbus</hi> are theſe babes,</l>
               <l>Or all the <hi>Iſra'litiſh</hi> youth?</l>
               <l>Say, In what fold of <hi>Purgatory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Purg'd in what ſtreams of fire or water,</l>
               <l>Are theſe <hi>Lambs</hi> whom this <hi>Fox</hi> did worry,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>dog</hi> ſlew? what can fancy flatter?</l>
               <l>Name me what <hi>canonized Saint and Martyr</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Annex'd this truth unto the Scriptures Charter.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170697:9"/>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Peace, <hi>Rachel,</hi> peace; do not deplore</l>
               <l>The murther of thy children, <hi>ſeeing</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They're not;</hi> yet are they not no more,</l>
               <l>And than thou gav'ſt have better being:</l>
               <l>VVeep not thy buds ſo ſoon do bleed</l>
               <l>Almoſt, as thou didſt them diſcloſe;</l>
               <l>They ſhould have grown here amongſt weed,</l>
               <l>Now flouriſh with their <hi>Jeſſe's roſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let <hi>Herod</hi> grieve for his ſon's death, and weep;</l>
               <l>Thou haſt no cauſe; then do not ſigh ſo deep.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt's being beheaded.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mark 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="27">27 And immediately Herod the king ſent an executioner, and commanded his head to be brought: and he went, and beheaded him in the priſon,</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170697:10"/>
                  <p n="28">28 And brought his head in a charger, and gave it to the damſel, and the damſel gave it to her mother.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>THrice-happie <hi>morning-ſtar,</hi> that didſt fore-run</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs</hi> his neer approach;</l>
               <l>As that <hi>Poſtilion</hi> precedes the Sun,</l>
               <l>And uſhers to the world his glorious Coach.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Blest Prodrom!</hi> who by th'art of <hi>Philip</hi> 's wife</l>
               <l>Didſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> fore-run in death, as well as life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Thrice-happie <hi>Jacob's Shiloh's Prolocutor!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bleſt <hi>Mercury</hi> to <hi>Jacob</hi>'s <hi>glorious Star;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our <hi>Saviour's Harbinger,</hi> the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Tutor,</l>
               <l>To ſhew their <hi>expectation</hi> was not far;</l>
               <l>Who in a purer ſtream then <hi>Jordan</hi>'s flood,</l>
               <l>At laſt baptiz'd thy Baptiſm with thy blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Curſt <hi>Herod!</hi> who as <hi>John Elijah</hi>'s ſpirit</l>
               <l>Had by a gracious influence bequeath'd;</l>
               <l>So thou, as by poſſeſſion, didſt inherit</l>
               <l>Thy father's rage, which here on <hi>John</hi> was breath'd.</l>
               <l>Hadſt thou no <hi>Trophee</hi> to adorn thy birth,</l>
               <l>But th' <hi>Baptiſt</hi>'s head? no triumph but ſuch mirth?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170697:10"/>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Bloody <hi>Herodias!</hi> that wert ſo rough,</l>
               <l>To recompenſe <hi>Iohn</hi>'s zeal with ſuch requitals:</l>
               <l>Was not thy <hi>Muſick</hi> ſpirited enough,</l>
               <l>Not joyn'd in conſort with the <hi>Baptiſt</hi>'s vitals?</l>
               <l>Never was <hi>Muſick</hi> of ſo groſs a crime</l>
               <l>Arraigned guilty, ſince old <hi>Iubal</hi>'s time.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Vile Wretch! who thus wouldſt make raſh <hi>Herod</hi>'s oath</l>
               <l>A Pander to a hot inceſt'ous Bed:</l>
               <l>Neither did <hi>Thomyris</hi> that famous <hi>Goth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As thou on <hi>Iohn</hi>'s, inſult on <hi>Cyrus</hi> head.</l>
               <l>Vile Monſter! thus to nuſtle up thy daughter,</l>
               <l>Ev'n from her tender yeers, to blood &amp; ſlaughter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wretch'd Damſel!</hi> thou whoſe too too active feet</l>
               <l>Were onely <hi>ſwift to ſhed the harmleſs blood</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of th' innocent:</hi> ev'n ſo a dancing Fleet</l>
               <l>Waits for her prey, while 't wantons on the flood.</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo a Hawk doth quaver in the air,</l>
               <l>Before ſhe ſouſe: ſo danc'd thy wicked pair.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Bleſt <hi>Iohn!</hi> as was <hi>Elijah,</hi> ſo wert thou</l>
               <l>Into a wilderneſs by fury baniſh'd;</l>
               <l>Both forc'd by women, both purſu'd by vow,</l>
               <l>Though both not in a fiery Chariot vaniſh'd.</l>
               <l>Yet herein thou an equal ſhare mayſt plead;</l>
               <l>Th'art member'd to a far more <hi>glorious Head.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170697:11"/>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Good God! how are we honour'd! that as <hi>John</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fore-ran to fit Chriſt's way before his face;</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo our Saviour, thy bleſſed Son,</l>
               <l>Prepares our way, and fits our reſting place:</l>
               <l>O let's ſucceed, where we ſhall be no other</l>
               <l>Then joynt-heirs with thy Son our <hi>elder brother.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the woman of Canaan.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="28">28 Then Jeſus anſwered and ſaid unto her, O woman, great is thy faith; be it unto thee even as thou wilt. And her daughter was made whole from that very hour.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>GOod-woman! who couldſt thus not only brook</l>
               <l>A ſtern diſdainful look,</l>
               <l>But the diſciples wrath, who held thy ſuit</l>
               <l>Some clamorous purſuit;</l>
               <l>As who would give no anſwer to a Cur,</l>
               <l>But with a ſtaff or ſpur.</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170697:11"/>
               <l>Nay, though that <hi>Chriſt</hi> retorted thy <hi>Lord help,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With no relief but <hi>Whelp,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And whom thou hop'dſt thy <hi>Advocate,</hi> we read,</l>
               <l>Did thus againſt thee plead:</l>
               <l>How heldſt thou his denials of thy want</l>
               <l>A prologue to a grant?</l>
               <l>As if repulſe were the propos'd condition</l>
               <l>To faith, before admiſſion.</l>
               <l>How by thy conſtancie was he eſteem'd</l>
               <l>Then moſt propitious, when he fartheſt ſeem'd?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>When he ſeem'd deaf, how thy importun'd prayer</l>
               <l>To muſick tun'd the ayr,</l>
               <l>And with ingeminated violence,</l>
               <l>Monopoliz'd his ſence?</l>
               <l>And when he ſeem'd to thee no leſs then dumb,</l>
               <l>How for thy faithful crumb,</l>
               <l>He having with his <hi>bread</hi> ſupply'd thy cauſe,</l>
               <l>Diſmiſs'd thee with applauſe.</l>
               <l>Denials made not thy affections froward,</l>
               <l>Nor yet thy zeal a coward.</l>
               <l>Thy quick-ey'd faith, ſmiles through <hi>his</hi> frowns did view,</l>
               <l>And through <hi>his</hi> wrath love knew:</l>
               <l>It through <hi>his</hi> threats an invitation ſaw,</l>
               <l>Which by repulſe did draw,</l>
               <l>And in the ſharp reproaches he avouch'd,</l>
               <l>Diſcern'd a welcome couch'd.</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170697:12"/>
               <l>Let others hope of Force, and boaſt of Fortune;</l>
               <l>When they ſhall fail, I gain when I importune.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>But how is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but now ſo much eſtranged,</l>
               <l>Now all to mercy changed?</l>
               <l>And thou, at firſt a <hi>dog,</hi> art now inrol'd</l>
               <l>One of his <hi>flock</hi> and <hi>fold.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For Faith's the mark by which his ſheep are known,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſuch ſaid he's thine own.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo wiſe <hi>Ioſeph</hi> held the <hi>ten</hi> for <hi>Spies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though brethren in his eyes;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Benjamin,</hi> whom he reputed chief,</l>
               <l>Purſu'd was for a thief</l>
               <l>But when he was diſclos'd, each threat of his</l>
               <l>Is changed to a kiſs;</l>
               <l>And for his late experimental check,</l>
               <l>Wept on his brothers neck.</l>
               <l>So as we ought to fear God's hand that ſavours</l>
               <l>Of peace, and ſuch-like favours:</l>
               <l>So ought we not deſpair: God oft doth frown,</l>
               <l>And ſeems then ſtrange, when <hi>he</hi> intends to crown.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Lord, what ſhe here would for her daughter have,</l>
               <l>I for my <hi>ſiſter</hi> crave:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> for my ſoul, and ſhe, the better <hi>I,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth for her body vie.</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170697:12"/>
               <l>That thou wouldſt diſpoſſeſs my <hi>haunted twins</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>legions</hi> of ſins;</l>
               <l>Which though perhaps not <hi>devils,</hi> yet the ſpawns</l>
               <l>Which here <hi>their father</hi> pawns.</l>
               <l>I'll not pray, <hi>If thou canſt;</hi> for, Lord, I know it,</l>
               <l>I know well thou canſt do it:</l>
               <l>Although with <hi>him</hi> I'll pray, with tears and grief,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord help my unbelief.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Come, purge thy Temple; let it not thus ſtink</l>
               <l>Like to a noyſom ſink.</l>
               <l>Lord, if thou wilt not hear me, I will force</l>
               <l>Thy mercy for remorſe.</l>
               <l>The <hi>unjuſt judge at length did hear her ſute;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why then 's <hi>the Iudge of all the world</hi> ſo mute?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the man heal'd at the pool of <hi>Betheſda.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="5">5 And a certain man was there, who had an infirmity thirty eight yeers.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170697:13"/>
                  <p n="6">6 When Jeſus ſaw him lie, and knew that he had been now a long time in that caſe, he ſaith unto him, Wilt thou be made whole?</p>
                  <p n="7">7 The impotent man anſwered him, Sir, I have no man when the water is troubled to put me into the pool; but while I am coming, another ſteppeth down before me.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Jeſus ſaith unto him, Ariſe, take up thy bed and walk.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 And immediately the man was made whole, and took up his bed and walked.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>AS one long wind-bound in the <hi>Cape of hope,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Until his gales</l>
               <l>Kinde <hi>Aeolus</hi> exhales,</l>
               <l>Bans the too faithful Cable-rope,</l>
               <l>And th' Anchors, which of Hope true <hi>emblems</hi> are,</l>
               <l>To him occaſion matter of deſpair:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>So lay thy patience at <hi>Betheſda</hi>'s pool,</l>
               <l>The ſoul ſo waits,</l>
               <l>Till death-divorcing ſtraits</l>
               <l>Shall waft her hence. So in a School,</l>
               <l>A full-ag'd youth, more ripe then rich, waits long</l>
               <l>Till wafted thence to th' <hi>Academick</hi> throng.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170697:13"/>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>The Tyde did ſerve thee often to thy will,</l>
               <l>By th' Angel mov'd,</l>
               <l>Not by the Moon improv'd:</l>
               <l>But gales of Love were wanting ſtill,</l>
               <l>To launch thee forth. So, far from Shore or Tyde,</l>
               <l>I've ſeen a ſhip lie on her uſeleſs ſide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>But who would not than thee much longer wait,</l>
               <l>If thus aſſur'd</l>
               <l>By Chriſt he ſhould be cur'd?</l>
               <l>And count all Phyſick but deceit.</l>
               <l>The vertue of this pool's not worth thy ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Compar'd with Chriſt the Well, and Well of life.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Oh who with <hi>Lazarus</hi> would not ſuſtain</l>
               <l>The pangs of death,</l>
               <l>Ev'n to their utmoſt breath,</l>
               <l>So by Chriſt to be rais'd again?</l>
               <l>Much more with thee who would not wait a time,</l>
               <l>With faithful patience, to be heal'd by him?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Lord, thus I well remember, when infected,</l>
               <l>Expecting ſtill</l>
               <l>Aid from the Doctor's ſtill,</l>
               <l>Which yet in vain I long expected:</l>
               <l>Yet evermore ſome paſſage intervenes,</l>
               <l>And robs me of my hope of outward means.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170697:14"/>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>While thus I lay like an <hi>expoſed elf,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>While death upbraids</l>
               <l>My hope of future aids,</l>
               <l>My <hi>beſt Phyſician</hi> came himſelf.</l>
               <l>Thus if thou come, let other Doctors ſtay,</l>
               <l>And I will fee them after for delay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>Lord, when my heart's thus <hi>troubled</hi> by thy <hi>Spirit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy <hi>South</hi> nor <hi>North</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can hardly launch me forth;</l>
               <l>Neither thy love nor wrath can ſtir it.</l>
               <l>I'm anchor'd to the world: but call the rocks,</l>
               <l>They'll come; but I ſtick faſt in leaden ſocks.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the Prodigal.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="20">20 And he aroſe, and came to his father: and when he was yet a great way off, his father ſaw him, and had compaſſion, and ran and fell on his neck, and kiſſed him.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170697:14"/>
                  <p n="21">21. And the ſon ſaid unto him, Father, I have ſinned againſt heaven, and in thy ſight, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſon.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>FOol-hardy <hi>Prodigal!</hi> what, couldſt not brook</l>
               <l>The diſc'pline of thy father's houſe,</l>
               <l>But wander'dſt like <hi>the errant ſpouſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ev'n as a ſheep that hath her fold forſook,</l>
               <l>Among the vagrant goats to brouze,</l>
               <l>From the tuition of her ſhepherds crook:</l>
               <l>VVhen in a ragged fleece,</l>
               <l>Each briar having ſnatch'd a peece,</l>
               <l>He's found and welcom'd as <hi>his Child or Neece.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Thus didſt thou rove &amp; rome, thus wert thou errant,</l>
               <l>Thus didſt thou from thy Father range,</l>
               <l>And leftſt his Palace from ſome grange;</l>
               <l>Thus thou embrac'dſt a ſtranger for thy Parent;</l>
               <l>Thy Native Land leftſt for one ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Till Death arreſts thee with a meagre warrant.</l>
               <l>No <hi>Confeſſor</hi> or <hi>Flamine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So can reduce, check or examine,</l>
               <l>Like th' <hi>Inquiſition</hi> of exacting famine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170697:15"/>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Thy wine is turn'd to tears, thy robes to rags:</l>
               <l>Thy Father did not get thy Portion</l>
               <l>By griping us'ry or extortion;</l>
               <l>That's not the cauſe th' haſt laviſht out thy bags,</l>
               <l>Yet he wo'n't count thee an abortion,</l>
               <l>Though his love draw thee not, but famine drags.</l>
               <l>Thy cates are turn'd to husks,</l>
               <l>To ordure thy Odours and Musks,</l>
               <l>Thy Songs to whines, thy greets to churliſh tusks.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Let theſe inducements thy return conſtrain.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Jacob</hi> kiſſed his loſt ſon.</l>
               <l>And <hi>David</hi> wandring <hi>Abſolon;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>Mary</hi> having often ſought in vain,</l>
               <l>Found and embrac'd her <hi>holy One,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As thou ſhalt be when thou returnſt again.</l>
               <l>The longing Soul of <hi>Kiſh</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ne'r did for <hi>Saul</hi> more ſtrongly wiſh,</l>
               <l>Nor welcome him with a more joyful diſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>'Twill be a <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> no return.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Abraham</hi> took his ſon repriev'd,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Shunamite</hi> ſo hers reviv'd,</l>
               <l>As thou ſhalt be receiv'd as from thy urn;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Naim</hi>'s widow took retriv'd</l>
               <l>Her ſons life, when Chriſt did his death adjourn.</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170697:15"/>
               <l>Dead <hi>Lazarus</hi> but kept</l>
               <l>His grave four dayes, as <hi>Martha</hi> wept;</l>
               <l>But thou haſt many yeers in darkneſs ſlept.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Should any one thy Father now inform</l>
               <l>Of a third brothers happy birth,</l>
               <l>It would adminiſter leſs mirth,</l>
               <l>Than that th'art regular, late ſo enorm.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Jacob</hi> bleſt that happy dearth,</l>
               <l>As he this famine. Let thy Brother ſtorm:</l>
               <l>Think why, where, what thou ſerveſt:</l>
               <l>Death here's thy wages, for thou ſtarveſt;</l>
               <l>Think on thy Fathers mercies, and his harveſts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>'Gainſt heav'n and in thy ſight I ſin have wrought,</l>
               <l>In ſuch a Di'lect couch thy ſhrift;</l>
               <l>Say of thy patrimonial gift,</l>
               <l>I've not <hi>one talent in a napkin</hi> brought;</l>
               <l>Not one to teſtifie my thrift:</l>
               <l>Then weep the meaning of each lab'ring thought:</l>
               <l>Say, thy dejected Spirit</l>
               <l>Counts thee not of ſuch worth and merit,</l>
               <l>To ſerve him, and much leſs, much leſs t' inherit.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170697:16"/>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Lord, I'm a prodigal, far worſe then this:</l>
               <l>When he away but once did rome</l>
               <l>Thou (we ne'er read) invit'dſt him home;</l>
               <l>But thou haſt often woo'd me with a <hi>Kiſs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet how unwillingly I come!</l>
               <l>Then threatſt me with <hi>a dearth</hi> far worſe then his:</l>
               <l>Yet I had rather whine,</l>
               <l>Then ſing; attend and feed with ſwine,</l>
               <l>Then with the Lamb to ſup, with thee to dine.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the Woman taken in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="3">3 And the Scribes and Phariſees brought unto him, a woman taken in adultery; and when they had ſet her in the midſt,</p>
                  <p n="4">4 They ſay unto him, Maſter, this woman was
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170697:16"/>taken in adultery, in the very act.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 Now Moſes in the law commanded us that ſuch ſhould be ſtoned: but what ſayeſt thou?</p>
                  <p n="7">7 So when they continued asking him, he lift up himſelf, and ſaid unto them. He that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, let him caſt the firſt ſtone at her.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>VIle <hi>Phar'ſees!</hi> who would make <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s truth the Pander</l>
               <l>T'accuſe <hi>him</hi> but with a more ſpecious ſlander</l>
               <l>His <hi>Statute-book</hi> hath no ſuch <hi>Law</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which doth vice both indulge and awe;</l>
               <l>Nor made <hi>Law</hi> of that kinde,</l>
               <l>Which both doth <hi>looſe and binde:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though your <hi>Law</hi> asks</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egyptian</hi> tasks,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which you will not ſo much</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As with one finger touch.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Juſtice</hi> is too ſtrict a <hi>Martial,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which is to ſin nor fond nor partial.</l>
               <l>And ſince man is too weak to ſatisfie</l>
               <l>His <hi>Father</hi>'s wrath, <hi>the Lord himſelf will die.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Yet your hypocriſie, falſe weights, and hins,</l>
               <l>Neglect of truth and love, are greater ſins;</l>
               <l>Which ere digeſted into fact</l>
               <l>He ſees, and much more in the act.</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170697:17"/>
               <l>Look how the womans luſt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s mercy writes in duſt,</l>
               <l>Which the next winde</l>
               <l>Blows out of minde.</l>
               <l>And yet, whate'er you claim,</l>
               <l>Your malice doth but aim</l>
               <l>To ſtone our <hi>Saviour</hi> in ſteed</l>
               <l>Of the adult'reſs, for the deed.</l>
               <l>And though you for her ſin do <hi>Law</hi> enforce,</l>
               <l>Your ſp'ritual adultery is worſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Your zeal may with her luſt go hand in hand;</l>
               <l>Both kindled were at one infernal brand.</l>
               <l>Your zeal's a particle of light</l>
               <l>Sprung from the gloomy Prince of night,</l>
               <l>When <hi>in an Angel's ſhape</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of light,</hi> he acts a rape.</l>
               <l>Your zeal is baud</l>
               <l>T'envie and fraud,</l>
               <l>As her Concupiſcence</l>
               <l>Was baud to this offence.</l>
               <l>'T is not true zeal, but hot-brain'd zanie,</l>
               <l>Which views each fault, ſquints through each crannie;</l>
               <l>To carp at others failings, but ſtill dallies</l>
               <l>With her own ſelf, nor ſees her craft and malice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Although ſome blaſphemouſly dare diſtruſt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s mother's honour, <hi>he</hi>'s no friend to luſt:</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170697:17"/>
               <l>With Harlots though he eats and drinks,</l>
               <l>He at their ſin connives nor winks.</l>
               <l>There's nothing now obſcene.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Mary Magdalene.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hell well enough</l>
               <l>Knows he's ſin-proof.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> may touch pitch, yet not</l>
               <l>Receive thereby a blot;</l>
               <l>And he with ſinners may converſe,</l>
               <l>Yet ne'er be tainted by commerce.</l>
               <l>And though <hi>Phyſitians</hi> need an <hi>Antidote</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ere they to ſick-men go, <hi>he</hi> wants them not.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Ev'n ſo would partial <hi>Judah Tamar</hi> ſtone,</l>
               <l>Till Shame retarded Reſolution:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Serpent,</hi> while he would implead</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Eve,</hi> receives a <hi>bruiſed head.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As hiſt by guilt and blame,</l>
               <l>Ye drop away for ſhame.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seth</hi>'s pillar ſtood</l>
               <l>So, when the flood,</l>
               <l>Wherein it late was drown'd,</l>
               <l>Was now departed round.</l>
               <l>As ſtands the woman thus alone,</l>
               <l>While you convicted all are gone;</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo ſtood weeping <hi>Niobe,</hi> when all</l>
               <l>Her hopeful ſons did by <hi>Apollo</hi> fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170697:18"/>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Th'art free, as if thy ſin were ne'er committed;</l>
               <l>Free as <hi>Suſanna,</hi> by that <hi>Childe</hi> acquitted:</l>
               <l>Th'art clear and clean from this offence,</l>
               <l>White as <hi>Suſanna</hi>'s innocence:</l>
               <l>And ſuch as hers I dare</l>
               <l>Say thy Accuſers are:</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Law</hi> inforce,</l>
               <l>Without remorſe:</l>
               <l>As they were hurried thence,</l>
               <l>So theſe, by Conſcience:</l>
               <l>Both out of malice, not true zeal,</l>
               <l>For ſentence unto <hi>Law</hi> appeal.</l>
               <l>Th'art clear'd by <hi>him</hi> whom thou haſt <hi>griev'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And who dares mention what thou ill haſt done?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Her luſt, deep in repentant tears is drench'd</l>
               <l>In waters which might <hi>Sodoms</hi> flames hav quench'd.</l>
               <l>How bitterly flows from her brain</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The former and the later rain!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not onely for this ſin:</l>
               <l>She doth for all begin</l>
               <l>To ſigh and ſob,</l>
               <l>To groan and throb.</l>
               <l>Were thus your malice rins'd,</l>
               <l>Y'had not been thus convinc'd.</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170697:18"/>
               <l>Her tears your malice may confound;</l>
               <l>They ſhew how deep her <hi>ſin is drown'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In the Seas depth.</hi> Nor doth it need your ſtones;</l>
               <l>Her fiſt, lo, beats her boſome till it grones.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>My ſoul's the <hi>woman,</hi> Lord, found guilty in</l>
               <l>The ſin of luſt, and in the luſt of ſin:</l>
               <l>And as the devil ſtill conſpires</l>
               <l>With my affections and deſires;</l>
               <l>So joyns with Conſcience</l>
               <l>To aggravate offence:</l>
               <l>Both ſue for ſentence</l>
               <l>Againſt repentance.</l>
               <l>Lord, at one word of thine,</l>
               <l>Their malice will decline.</l>
               <l>No <hi>Ottacus</hi> on thy acquittance,</l>
               <l>Will to thy court ſue for admittance.</l>
               <l>From ſin and guilt thus cleared when I die,</l>
               <l>I ſhall ſtand free, and <hi>none but thee and I.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On <hi>Mary Magdalene.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="6">6 Now when Jeſus was in Bethany, in the houſe of Simon the leper,</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170697:19"/>
                  <p n="7">7 There came unto him a woman having an alabaſter-box of very precious ointment, and poured it on his head as he ſate at meat.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>BLeſt <hi>Mary!</hi> whoſe repentant rheums</l>
               <l>Were far more precious then thy <hi>Nard:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy tears nor age nor time conſumes,</l>
               <l>Which waſtes and dries the richeſt <hi>Lard.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Nard</hi> afforded rich perfumes;</l>
               <l>Thy vocal tears each where are heard.</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Nard</hi> which on <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s head did fleet,</l>
               <l>Though grateful to him, was leſs ſweet</l>
               <l>Then were the tears wherwith thou bath'dſt his feet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>The rich ingredient which thy tears</l>
               <l>Gave to thy <hi>Nard,</hi> ſurpaſs'd all alms,</l>
               <l>Though of continuance of years:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>True tears are of themſelves a balm,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Nard</hi> foreſtalling both his ears,</l>
               <l>Preſents each groan a Mercy-pſalm.</l>
               <l>See, he accepts thy love and thee,</l>
               <l>Nor doth at all eſteem't to be,</l>
               <l>T'anoint th' <hi>Anointed,</hi> a <hi>Tautologie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170697:19"/>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Do not eſteem't an act uncouth,</l>
               <l>Falſe-hearted <hi>Judas,</hi> what ſhe doth.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Eli</hi> marked <hi>Hannah</hi>'s mouth.</l>
               <l>And with her cauſleſly was wroth.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Boreas</hi> chides the healing <hi>South:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So on the <hi>Church boors frend and froth.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lov'dſt thou the poor, yet wert ſo ſpeedy</l>
               <l>To proſecute them, and ſo greedy,</l>
               <l>To ſell thy Maſter that was <hi>poor and needy?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>As Ice to Cryſtal is congeal'd,</l>
               <l>That it nor ſun nor fire can melt;</l>
               <l>So ſeem our hearts and eye-balls ſeal'd</l>
               <l>To hardneſs, that no grief is felt.</l>
               <l>Our froſt-bound hearts lie ſtill conceal'd:</l>
               <l>Let Love inflame, or Anger ſwell't:</l>
               <l>Yet tears can't blinde, nor watry cries</l>
               <l>Diſſolve the gelly of our eyes,</l>
               <l>No more then rain can melt the Cryſtal skies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Good-woman! who eſteem'd no paint</l>
               <l>Like to a face blubber'd with tears;</l>
               <l>All other tinctures are but faint,</l>
               <l>But theſe out-wear all age and yeers.</l>
               <l>No <hi>Venus</hi>-mole beſpeaks a Saint,</l>
               <l>No <hi>beauty-spot</hi> like theſe appears.</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170697:20"/>
               <l>And as the <hi>Moon</hi>'s each thinner place</l>
               <l>Shews ſomewhat dark, yet no diſgrace:</l>
               <l>True tears ſo never ſtain a beauteous face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>For ſin, hair-rending fingers ought</l>
               <l>To be our onely criſping-pins:</l>
               <l>Although indeed our hair's too ſoft</l>
               <l>To make a hair-cloth for our skins.</l>
               <l>No powder is like aſhes thought,</l>
               <l>To roll our treſſes in for ſins.</l>
               <l>Hair is the moiſture of the brain,</l>
               <l>And ſo are tears: then 'twere not vain</l>
               <l>With <hi>Mary</hi> here, to mix them once again.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Thrice-bleſſed Convert! from whoſe breſt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> having ſeven devils caſt,</l>
               <l>Left not thy boſome unpoſſeſt,</l>
               <l>But there the ſpirit of Grief plac'd.</l>
               <l>The former made thee worſe then beaſt,</l>
               <l>The later gave thee reſt at laſt.</l>
               <l>Oh were I ſo poſſeſs'd! theſe fits</l>
               <l>Beſpeak us beſt to b'in our wits:</l>
               <l>No joy ſhould chaſe it by removal-Writs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>For <hi>Lazarus</hi> my outward man,</l>
               <l>If ſick, my <hi>Mary,</hi> Lord, can mourn;</l>
               <l>Groan like a dove, throb like a ſwan,</l>
               <l>Till thou haſt rais'd him from his urn:</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170697:20"/>
               <l>But for her ſelf <hi>ſhe</hi> now and than</l>
               <l>Can weep, but doth her grief adjourn.</l>
               <l>And yet we ſee, when thou doſt move</l>
               <l>Womens devotions unto love,</l>
               <l>Man ever doth the weaker veſſel prove.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On <hi>Peter</hi>'s denial of his Maſter.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 26.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="74">74 And Peter remembred the words of Jeſus, which ſaid unto him, Before the cock crow, thou ſhalt deny me thrice. And he went out, and wept bitterly.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>WHat, <hi>Peter,</hi> haſt deny'd thy <hi>Maſter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In his diſaſter?</l>
               <l>Couldſt not withſtand, thou eaſie <hi>rock,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So ſmall a ſhock?</l>
               <l>Loor'd thy foundation from beneath,</l>
               <l>At a maids breath?</l>
               <l>Thou <hi>bear a Church?</hi> who wert thy ſelf</l>
               <l>A ſandy ſhelf,</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Chriſt</hi> t'a rock confirm'd thy gravel,</l>
               <l>Which none could ravel.</l>
               <l>Thee, rather then a <hi>rock,</hi> we ſtile,</l>
               <l>For thy inconſtancie, A <hi>floating Ile.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170697:21"/>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Weak fiſher of men! if thus caught</l>
               <l>At a maids draught:</l>
               <l>How wilt thou hence oppoſe the harms</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Mermaids</hi> charms?</l>
               <l>If thee ſo much this common frie</l>
               <l>Did terrifie;</l>
               <l>How will the huge <hi>Leviathan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or th' <hi>Hurricane?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How wilt withſtand that <hi>Polypheme,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſpouts a ſtream</l>
               <l>Of fury on all Chriſtian matters,</l>
               <l>Diſturbs your rivers, and pollutes your waters?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>If thou wert put to ſuch extremes</l>
               <l>On tender ſtreams,</l>
               <l>How wilt thou ſtand it on thoſe Seas</l>
               <l>That know no pleas?</l>
               <l>How wilt oppoſe thoſe <hi>Zyphia's</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Remora's?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When Seas with angry windes do ſurge,</l>
               <l>When tempeſts purge,</l>
               <l>Unleſs that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ariſe, like that</l>
               <l>Mount <hi>Ararat;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How quickly will the raging billows</l>
               <l>Make Seas your Down-bed, and the Rocks your pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170697:21"/>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Are all thy promiſes ſo toward</l>
               <l>So ſoon turn'd coward!</l>
               <l>When of thy love there ſhould be proof,</l>
               <l>Thou ſtoodſt aloof:</l>
               <l>And yet thy fortitude, I wote,</l>
               <l>Was more remote.</l>
               <l>Was all thy valour but t' attend</l>
               <l>To ſee the end?</l>
               <l>More fickle far then was the maid</l>
               <l>Which thee betraid:</l>
               <l>She not deny'd her words, while thou</l>
               <l>Didſt <hi>ſtart aſide like a deceitful bowe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Look, <hi>Peter,</hi> look, thy Maſter's <hi>minion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How <hi>Chriſt</hi> they pinion,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Judas</hi> treaſon, and thy fear:</l>
               <l>He's captiv'd here,</l>
               <l>Whom (worſe then <hi>Jewiſh</hi> rage and ſcorn)</l>
               <l>Thou haſt forſworn.</l>
               <l>Two have bely'd him even now</l>
               <l>By perjur'd vow:</l>
               <l>But thou haſt him deny'd far worſe,</l>
               <l>By oath and curſe.</l>
               <l>Heark, heark, how ſprightly <hi>Chaunticleer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Proclaims thee coward for thy daſtard-fear.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170697:22"/>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Look with what <hi>glance</hi> thy Saviour eyes</l>
               <l>Thy perjuries:</l>
               <l>Let <hi>it</hi> diſſolve thy frozen fears</l>
               <l>To melting tears.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Marah</hi>-waters be alone</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Helicone;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not <hi>Sodom</hi>'s lake, tears groſs and thick,</l>
               <l>But ſharp and quick.</l>
               <l>And as the <hi>Pontick Ocean</hi>'s pride</l>
               <l>Ne'er ebbes by Tide;</l>
               <l>Let tears ne'er ebbe, but ever riſe,</l>
               <l>Till they have got the cuſtom of thy eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>In <hi>Lot's wife's obelisk of ſalt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Go read thy fault;</l>
               <l>And let <hi>it</hi> all thy moiſture ſeaſon</l>
               <l>To tears for treaſon.</l>
               <l>But if thy holy ſorrow luſts</l>
               <l>For ſharper guſts,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt's vinegar and gall</hi> would fitter</l>
               <l>Thy grief imbitter.</l>
               <l>With ſuch intoxications whole,</l>
               <l>Go drench thy ſoul.</l>
               <l>Confeſs him with the <hi>penitent thief;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And as th' haſt freez'd for fear, go melt for grief.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170697:22"/>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Good God! our weakneſs will without thee,</l>
               <l>Not onely doubt thee,</l>
               <l>But of thee make a flat denial,</l>
               <l>On eaſie trial;</l>
               <l>Nay, ſhall not onely thus deny thee,</l>
               <l>But ſhall defie thee.</l>
               <l>If th' <hi>rock</hi> could not withſtand theſe floats.</l>
               <l>Can empty boats?</l>
               <l>If that ſuch casks ſoon buoy'd thy <hi>rock,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like ſome light block.</l>
               <l>Can we hold out, who of our ſelves</l>
               <l>No anch'rage have, but onely ſands and ſhelves?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the Paſsion and Death of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Zech. 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="10">10 And they ſhall look upon me whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him, as one mourneth for his onely ſon; and ſhall be in bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170697:23"/>for him, as one that is in bitterneſs for his firſt-born.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw hath bright <hi>Phoebus,</hi> through his heat,</l>
               <l>Drawn up a cloud of vapours, which do threat</l>
               <l>T'obſcure his glorious face; and therefore muſter</l>
               <l>Their pitchie beds, to ſmother up his luſter.</l>
               <l>God long <hi>hath rebels nouriſh'd,</hi> who now further,</l>
               <l>From damn'd rebellion proceed to murther.</l>
               <l>Could not your ſins be dy'd enough in grain,</l>
               <l>From all the Prophets, but from ſuch a vain?</l>
               <l>Could not the meaſure of your ſins be fill'd</l>
               <l>In murth'ring them, except their God you kill'd?</l>
               <l>Was this to make your <hi>crimſon, wooll,</hi> (vile brood)</l>
               <l>To bathe the <hi>Lamb</hi> thus in his crimſon blood?</l>
               <l>We do't by application, thus being done:</l>
               <l>But meant you ſo in your intention?</l>
               <l>Was your damnation of ſo groſs a weight,</l>
               <l>That nought could raiſe the ſcales t'an equal height,</l>
               <l>But ſuch an act as this? O curſed ſtir!</l>
               <l>The <hi>Saw's in arms againſt the Carpenter.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was't not enough thou wert in fleſh benum'd,</l>
               <l>But when thy yeers t'a perfect age th' hadſt ſum'd,</l>
               <l>Bleſt <hi>Vine,</hi> were thy ripe grapes ſmote by the rod,</l>
               <l>And in thy <hi>Father's angry wine-preſs trod.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Curs'd <hi>Olivet!</hi> bear, hence, no fruit nor leaf,</l>
               <l>Nor in thy vale be cropt a fruitful ſheaf.</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170697:23"/>
               <l>Unhappie mount, fatal to <hi>Abſalon;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>David</hi> once, now to his <hi>glorious Son,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By <hi>Judah</hi>'s fraud. Here <hi>David</hi> mourn'd and wept,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Jeſus</hi> here his mourning veſper kept.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gethſemane!</hi> may neither <hi>dew nor rain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hence dy thy garden in a verdant grain:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Jeſſe's Roſe,</hi> pluck'd from thy teeming breſt,</l>
               <l>Was raviſh'd hence by that <hi>rebellious beast.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here roar'd the <hi>Lion;</hi> in this diſmal grove,</l>
               <l>The <hi>princely Eagle mourned like a dove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As the condoling heavens, from the skie,</l>
               <l>Weep blood, as <hi>Omen</hi> of ſome <hi>Prodigie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So, in his paſſion, an exceſſive heat</l>
               <l>Forc'd th'row his bleſſed pores a bloody ſweat.</l>
               <l>Who by his word foil'd hell, could not ſuſtain</l>
               <l>The weight of ſin without this heavie pain.</l>
               <l>And this proves true his moan i' th' ſacred leaves:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I am ſin burthen'd, as a cart by ſheaves.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here was the Lord of hoſts ſurpriz'd and taken</l>
               <l>By Romane forces; here by 's friends forſaken.</l>
               <l>Bleſt <hi>Saviour!</hi> what, couldſt thou not command</l>
               <l>A <hi>with'ring dryneſs on each treach'rous hand?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Couldſt thou ſend <hi>fire from heaven</hi> at his clauſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If I'm a man of God,</hi> to plead thy cauſe,</l>
               <l>Twice following on <hi>the captains and their fifty;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And of thy vengeance wert thou here ſo thrifty?</l>
               <l>Didſt thou benight the <hi>Syrians eyes who came</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To ſeize that Prophet, when he beg'd the ſame?</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170697:24"/>
               <l>Yet did thy <hi>Majeſtie</hi> thus humbly ſtoop</l>
               <l>To the ſurpriſal of ſo ſmall a Troop?</l>
               <l>Accurſed <hi>Judas!</hi> had <hi>Cham</hi> in the flood</l>
               <l>So guilty been of treaſon and of blood,</l>
               <l>H' had drown'd the <hi>Ark,</hi> with all the reſt. At firſt,</l>
               <l>God with ſterility, in part, th'earth accurſt,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Adam</hi>'s ſin: and could we look for leſs,</l>
               <l>For thy curs'd ſake, then total barrenneſs?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Abſtract of wickedneſs!</hi> For if had <hi>Cain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>mother</hi> raviſh'd, and his <hi>father</hi> ſlain,</l>
               <l>Thou wert more guilty, in juſt balance weigh'd,</l>
               <l>Who haſt unnat'rally thy <hi>Lord</hi> betraid.</l>
               <l>Wretch'd <hi>Pilate!</hi> what, did not thy conſcience grudge</l>
               <l>Againſt thy tongue, when thou condemn'ſt thy Judge,</l>
               <l>Who could have doom'd thee, for thy horrid crime,</l>
               <l>Unto the ſhameful Tree prepar'd for him?</l>
               <l>But thus hath God decreed: doſt thou not ſentence</l>
               <l>Thy haſty doom with a too late repentance?</l>
               <l>Accurs'd <hi>Jeruſalem!</hi> the bloody ſtage</l>
               <l>Of wanton murther, and inconſtant rage:</l>
               <l>Fell not the juſt reſults of <hi>Hiel</hi>'s guilt</l>
               <l>On <hi>Aelius,</hi> who ſo vile a town rebuilt?</l>
               <l>You would no king but <hi>Caeſar:</hi> in concluſion,</l>
               <l>Who but a <hi>Caeſar</hi> was your juſt confuſion?</l>
               <l>Accurſed <hi>Calvary!</hi> henceforward we</l>
               <l>Will never curſe from <hi>Ebal,</hi> but from thee.</l>
               <l>May envious Mice hence gnaw thee from the Map:</l>
               <l>For here the <hi>Branch</hi> was rob'd of fruit and ſap.</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170697:24"/>
               <l>But why d' I curſe? Each place a <hi>Gerizim,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By theſe his bleſſed pains, is made by him.</l>
               <l>And my ſin with the Souldiers, hand in hand,</l>
               <l>Betraid my <hi>Saviour,</hi> and bid him ſtand.</l>
               <l>Mine mock'd, mine ſcourg'd him too: my ſins in groſs</l>
               <l>Help'd, with the Jews, to nail him on the Croſs.</l>
               <l>I know not whe'er my heart ſhould dance or bleed</l>
               <l>At this, this ſo accurſed bleſſed deed.</l>
               <l>O for a fancy at his ſhameful death,</l>
               <l>To curſe and bleſs theſe actions in a breath!</l>
               <l>I ſhould not call <hi>good ill,</hi> nor <hi>evil good;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For both are ſo, as they are underſtood.</l>
               <l>And now, methinks, I ſee him on the Croſs:</l>
               <l>What ſhall I deſcant? what define or gloſs?</l>
               <l>Forgive my murth'ring Fancy; 't is no Jew,</l>
               <l>Although it feign thee crucifi'd in view.</l>
               <l>I'll riſe in ſpight of their confuſed ſwarms,</l>
               <l>And beg th' embracement of his outſtretch'd arms:</l>
               <l>Nor will I ceaſe, till I've that promiſe made</l>
               <l>To me, which even now bleſt <hi>Giſmas</hi> had.</l>
               <l>I'll kiſs his lips, embrace his glorious neck;</l>
               <l>But not unnail him fearing <hi>Peter</hi>'s check;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Get thee behinde me, Satan: for this favour</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Doth not of heaven, but of Satan ſavour.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'll ſuck his crimſon wounds, till I have found</l>
               <l>My glutton-ſoul is tinctur'd from each wound.</l>
               <l>I'll ſtrive t' outweep his wounds: and leſt it breed</l>
               <l>Diſtake I bleed not too, my heart ſhall bleed.</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170697:25"/>
               <l>But lo, the Sun's eclips'd, withdraws his ray,</l>
               <l>And all in <hi>mourning darkneſs</hi> clothes the day.</l>
               <l>And durſt the ſtars to ſhine? have they endur'd</l>
               <l>To ſee <hi>the Star of Jacob</hi> thus obſcur'd?</l>
               <l>No, beauteous light (as if that now were furl'd</l>
               <l>Heav'ns gaudy curtains) hath forſook the world,</l>
               <l>Not with the luſtre of a <hi>Comet</hi> fring'd;</l>
               <l>And th' earth, as by an earthquake, ſeems unhing'd.</l>
               <l>At which (as frighted from that ſweet repoſe)</l>
               <l>The <hi>Saints</hi> that ſlept long in their graves, aroſe:</l>
               <l>The Temple's veil 's rent from the top to th' roof;</l>
               <l>For why? its <hi>Type</hi> is rent and pierced through.</l>
               <l>Now is well-nigh our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s ſoul extorted,</l>
               <l>His body thus by wounds and nails ſupported:</l>
               <l>Nor was his bodies weight ſo great, as were</l>
               <l>Our ſins, which he upon his ſoul did bear.</l>
               <l>Hark, how his ſoul's expired with a cry:</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſin's ſo great, to cauſe a God to die?</l>
               <l>Not his: for he appeals to th' envious Jews;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which of you can me of a ſin accuſe?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And even <hi>Pilate, Ceſar's wicked groom,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Did clear his inn'cence ere he clear'd his doom.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We ſin'd in the <hi>firſt Adam,</hi> and depriv'd</l>
               <l>The <hi>ſecond</hi> of his life, all, ere we liv'd:</l>
               <l>But gracious mercy (as <hi>Rebekka</hi>'s twins,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jacob and Eſau</hi>) ſtrugled with our ſins</l>
               <l>In the womb of Eternity; and thus</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Smooth mercy</hi> did ſupplant <hi>rough ſin</hi> for us:</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170697:25"/>
               <l>And thus the birth-right's ours, our title's good:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Chriſt</hi> ev'n now hath ſeal'd it with his blood.</l>
               <l>Now hath the Sun with more then common haſte</l>
               <l>(Scarf'd in his Sphere) deſcended <hi>Veſta</hi>'s waſte,</l>
               <l>And (as hence frighted) of ſuch acts as theſe</l>
               <l>Hath carried news to the <hi>Antipodes.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here for a time though we <hi>in darkneſs grope,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let's not deſpair, <hi>as men being void of hope:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, ſurer then the Sun will riſe, though ſlain,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Sun of righteouſneſs</hi> will riſe again.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the good Thief.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="43">43 And Jeſus ſaid unto him Verily I ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, This day ſhalt thou be with me in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>WHat ſhall I gloſs,</l>
               <l>Good <hi>Giſmas,</hi> on thy Croſs?</l>
               <l>Why may it reſemble not</l>
               <l>To the tree of <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Chariot?</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170697:26"/>
               <l>By which,</l>
               <l>To th' higheſt pitch</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt b' advanc'd of bliſs:</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Jacob</hi>'s ladder 't is,</l>
               <l>Where Angels ſtand</l>
               <l>At hand.</l>
               <l>Thy Croſs is but a type how Chriſt thy ſoul</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This day</hi> will fix above each pole.</l>
               <l>O happie puniſhment,</l>
               <l>Beyond extent!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Did <hi>Barabbas</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Know who our Saviour was,</l>
               <l>He'd ſcorn his life: that Jewiſh favour</l>
               <l>Would in his choice no reliſh finde, or ſavour:</l>
               <l>But beg'd,</l>
               <l>By Conſcience egg'd,</l>
               <l>That he might ſpell him yet,</l>
               <l>Their ears how would he fret?</l>
               <l>Accuſe that throng</l>
               <l>Of wrong?</l>
               <l>That Chriſt's blood ſpilt ſurpaſs'd that deed of <hi>Cain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'T would dye <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in grain;</l>
               <l>That they had now gone further</l>
               <l>Than <hi>he</hi> in murther.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Good Thief, from whence</l>
               <l>Knew'ſt thou Chriſt? not from Senſe:</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170697:26"/>
               <l>Pain 's no reſpirer: its extremes</l>
               <l>No reſpite gives to think on ſerious Themes.</l>
               <l>No, 't was</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The winde</hi> of grace,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which as it breathes on men</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Where it doth pleaſe:</hi> ſo when.</l>
               <l>Which here did breath</l>
               <l>In death:</l>
               <l>So through a day ſo dark, that I might ſay</l>
               <l>A ling'ring twilight 't were, no day;</l>
               <l>I've ſeen the ſetting Sun</l>
               <l>Diſplay'd anon,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>O happie time</l>
               <l>Thou di'dſt now for thy crime.</l>
               <l>So have I ſeen a neighb'ring cloud,</l>
               <l>Th'row which the Sun ſeem'd to look beetle-brow'd,</l>
               <l>Ere night</l>
               <l>Sun-burnt ſo bright,</l>
               <l>As thou by ſuff'ring neer</l>
               <l>The <hi>righteous Phoebus</hi> here,</l>
               <l>Thus grew'ſt acquainted,</l>
               <l>Thus Sainted:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> of thy ſhame partook, thou of his glory;</l>
               <l>Bleſt change, beyond conceit or ſtory!</l>
               <l>Thy Croſs each wiſe Invention</l>
               <l>Stiles thy Aſcention.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170697:27"/>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laverna</hi> now</l>
               <l>No longer hath thy vow:</l>
               <l>But he alone hath thy belief,</l>
               <l>Whoſe inn'cence ſuffers with thee as a Thief.</l>
               <l>This craft</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> thee hath taught,</l>
               <l>To rob hell of her aim.</l>
               <l>Though Death not of her claim;</l>
               <l>Not to redeem</l>
               <l>eſteem:</l>
               <l>For thou giv'ſt Chriſt the praiſe, thy ſelf the ſhame,</l>
               <l>Though <hi>Diſmas</hi> doth blaſpheme his name,</l>
               <l>And, ev'n in death, pants</l>
               <l>His wicked taunts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Peace, <hi>Satan's martyr,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though Chriſt nor law nor charter</l>
               <l>Hath broke, the Scriptures have not ſlumber'd,</l>
               <l>Which have foretold that Chriſt muſt thus be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber'd.</l>
               <l>But if</l>
               <l>Th' hadſt been no Thief,</l>
               <l>Chriſt had, t' appeaſe their pride,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Barabbas</hi> thus di'd,</l>
               <l>In equipage</l>
               <l>Of rage:</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170697:27"/>
               <l>But now thy theft 's in grain; thou doſt contract</l>
               <l>Blood to 't, while thou approv'ſt their act:</l>
               <l>And while thou ſhouldſt condole,</l>
               <l>Doſt vex his ſoul.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Didſt never read?</l>
               <l>Good thief, lift up thy head;</l>
               <l>With th' eye of faith look, and condole</l>
               <l>The <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> on you curſed pole.</l>
               <l>The grief</l>
               <l>Thou wert a Thief,</l>
               <l>Did wound his ſoul more fierce</l>
               <l>Then nail or ſpear can pierce.</l>
               <l>How for thy deeds</l>
               <l>He bleeds!</l>
               <l>His <hi>bloody ſweat,</hi> ſweat through each gracious pore,</l>
               <l>Claims but unfeigned tears, no more;</l>
               <l>His giving up the ghoſt,</l>
               <l>But ſighs at moſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Thy Scripture's, Lord,</l>
               <l>Thy gracious Record,</l>
               <l>That <hi>ſhining light</hi> which through the dark</l>
               <l>Directs us <hi>in our race unto that mark.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But this</l>
               <l>Thy paſſage is</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170697:28"/>
               <l>A circumſtance more ample</l>
               <l>For precept then example:</l>
               <l>We finde this one</l>
               <l>Alone,</l>
               <l>Whoſe late repentance Chriſt in death vouchſaf'd:</l>
               <l>Although thy wiſdom hath me taught</l>
               <l>This Scene not to prorogue</l>
               <l>Till th' <hi>Epilogue.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the Reſurrection of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Cnriſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="5">5 And the angel anſwered and ſaid to the woman, Fear not: for I know that ye ſeek Jeſus which was crucified.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 He is not here: for he is riſen, as he ſaid. Come, ſee the place where the Lord lay.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170697:28"/>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>ARiſe, my active ſoul, and run;</l>
               <l>Keep meaſure with <hi>you dancing Sun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who ſeems as weary of his Sphere,</l>
               <l>As thou to be confined here:</l>
               <l>Look, how his ſprightly beams do ſpark:</l>
               <l>So <hi>David</hi> danc'd before the <hi>Ark.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How he deſcends his Chariot! he, in this,</l>
               <l>Worſhips Chriſt's riſing, as the <hi>Perſian</hi> his.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>But why doth <hi>Phoebus</hi> mount his head</l>
               <l>So ſoon up from <hi>Aurora</hi> 's bed?</l>
               <l>The tother night, when we, my ſoul,</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Saviour</hi> 's Paſſion did condole,</l>
               <l>The frighted Sun forſook our clime</l>
               <l>Two hours before his wonted time;</l>
               <l>And therefore now the ſooner gilds the heaven,</l>
               <l>By two hours time, to make his courſe up even.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>But how rid <hi>Satan</hi> and his <hi>Legions</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In triumph th'row th' infernal Regions?</l>
               <l>The Sp'rits which Chriſt out-caſt, did come,</l>
               <l>With Songs of triumph on his Tomb:</l>
               <l>All mankinde was proſcrib'd; whom death</l>
               <l>Did in conceit to hell bequeath.</l>
               <l>Oh how death gloried that all now was ſafe!</l>
               <l>And hell in triumph wrote his Epitaph.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170697:29"/>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>How did the Devil Man upbraid,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Christ</hi> ſo weakly was betraid?</l>
               <l>And he who <hi>took not Angels ſeed,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But Abraham's,</hi> fail'd in the deed;</l>
               <l>And by that ſeed ſpurn'd to his grave,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>he</hi> in mercy came to ſave.</l>
               <l>That now the <hi>God of life</hi> was dead, this mirth</l>
               <l>Had balm to cure the wounds made by <hi>his</hi> birth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>But <hi>Satan,</hi> at the third days dawn,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> now hath re-aſſum'd his pawn.</l>
               <l>Thoughtſt thou on <hi>his</hi> t' inſult, as once</l>
               <l>Thou proudly didſt for <hi>Moſes</hi> bones?</l>
               <l>Thy two days triumph 's like the ſtory</l>
               <l>Of the <hi>Perſian pris'ners glory.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So thought the <hi>Gazites Samſon</hi> ſafe, till day,</l>
               <l>When he aroſe, and bore the gates away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Deſcend, damn'd ſp'rits; as you began,</l>
               <l>Howl on. The death of <hi>great God Pan,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At this <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s conqueſt, we may call</l>
               <l>Your ruine, <hi>Satans ſecond fall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Come, <hi>King of terrours,</hi> yeeld thy <hi>trophies</hi>
               </l>
               <l>On <hi>Heroes, Souldiers,</hi> and <hi>Sophies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Unto our <hi>Saviour;</hi> for thou art undone;</l>
               <l>Thy Triumph 's but an empty <hi>Skeleton.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170697:29"/>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>My ſoul, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was born, nay di'd,</l>
               <l>Did not ſo much quench <hi>Satan</hi> 's pride:</l>
               <l>But when he roſe, this bleſſed morn,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hell</hi> was confounded, <hi>Death</hi> forlorn.</l>
               <l>Were 't not for what this day brings forth,</l>
               <l>The <hi>reſt</hi> had loſt that ſolemn worth.</l>
               <l>Hence, on this day let no foul ſpirit dare</l>
               <l>T' aſcend the Regions of our earth or air.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Lord, as by <hi>thine</hi> I am aſſur'd</l>
               <l>My bodies riſe ſhall be procur'd:</l>
               <l>So, let my ſoul feel 't here begin</l>
               <l>Her reſurrection too from ſin.</l>
               <l>Lord, 'tis too much ſhe's thus confin'd:</l>
               <l>But is ſhe buried in this kinde?</l>
               <l>Oh raiſe her up: if thus thou pleaſe to do,</l>
               <l>My heart <hi>(my bodies Sun)</hi> ſhall triumph too.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170697:30"/>
            <head>On the Aſcenſion of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 24.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="8">8. Lift up your heads, O ye gates, and be ye lift up ye everlasting doors, and the King of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall come in.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Who is the King of glory? even the Lord of hoſts he is the King of glory.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>YE <hi>bleſt immortals,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Divide your glorious portals.</l>
               <l>Who not dilates</l>
               <l>The everlaſting gates,</l>
               <l>While that the <hi>King of glory</hi> mounts his throne?</l>
               <l>Though <hi>by his own</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here nor receiv'd nor known:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We rather worry</l>
               <l>The <hi>bleſſed Lamb of glory.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your <hi>Wiſdom</hi> knows him <hi>God's eternal Son.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170697:30"/>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>His work is ended,</l>
               <l>Nought partial or ſuſpended.</l>
               <l>Bleſt Angels too,</l>
               <l>He purchas'd hath for you</l>
               <l>A nature fix'd, which ſeem'd before unfiniſh'd.</l>
               <l>And of a <hi>worm</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though here he took the form;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It,</hi> ſince he di'd,</l>
               <l>Is ſo much glorifi'd,</l>
               <l>His <hi>Godhead</hi> 's neither clouded nor diminiſh'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>'T is now no <hi>Shrine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>T' <hi>his Godhead</hi> more divine:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His</hi> glorious fleſh</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> needs not now refreſh</l>
               <l>With food or reſt, from hunger or from labour.</l>
               <l>And if he here</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shone on the mount ſo clear,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if the <hi>Sun</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With rays his coat had ſpun;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How brighter ſhines <hi>he</hi> now than on mount <hi>Tabor!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Since <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſo clear</l>
               <l>Shines in <hi>his Manhood</hi>'s Sphere,</l>
               <l>That at its graces</l>
               <l>Ye <hi>Angels hide your faces:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170697:31"/>
               <l>See in the <hi>Trinities tranſparent myrrour</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How <hi>he</hi> 's inſtal'd,</l>
               <l>And in <hi>his</hi> robes impall'd;</l>
               <l>How he 's renown'd,</l>
               <l>And by <hi>his Father</hi> crown'd</l>
               <l>With <hi>gracious Majestie,</hi> and awful terrour.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>At his return,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pearlie gates do burn;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shines with each kinde of Gem;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>new Jeruſalem</hi> with glory burniſht:</l>
               <l>Nought here is built</l>
               <l>With ſuperficial gilt;</l>
               <l>But all in gold</l>
               <l>The Citie is inrol'd;</l>
               <l>All thus againſt <hi>his</hi> bleſt <hi>Aſcention</hi> furniſht.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Of <hi>Precious ſtones</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are her foundations;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Her Pearlie ſtreets</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Do brandiſh beaming ſheets,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reflecting from the <hi>Lamb</hi>'s moſt glorious face.</l>
               <l>Here 's conſtant noon,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No need of Sun or Moon:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our glim'ring <hi>Globe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deck'd in his azur'd robe,</l>
               <l>Here an Eclipſe were to the loweſt <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170697:31"/>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>How are we bleſt!</l>
               <l>That have ſo ſweet a reſt</l>
               <l>Got by the care</l>
               <l>Of ſuch a <hi>Harbinger,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who all things can command, all conſummate.</l>
               <l>The way to heaven</l>
               <l>He hath made plain and even;</l>
               <l>And what with thorns</l>
               <l>Was choak'd, his grace adorns</l>
               <l>With roſe-beds, &amp; makes wide heav'ns <hi>narrow gate.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>As <hi>Olivet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some ſay, retains as yet</l>
               <l>Thy foot 's laſt print,</l>
               <l>That nought can cloſe the dint:</l>
               <l>Grave on my ſtupid ſoul (Lord) this days love,</l>
               <l>Ev'n at the mention</l>
               <l>Of this thy bleſt aſcention:</l>
               <l>Let her aſpire,</l>
               <l>Like an excentrick fire,</l>
               <l>To <hi>thee</hi> her Centre that art fix'd above.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170697:32"/>
            <head>On Chriſt his Seſſion at the right hand of God.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mark 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="19">19 So then, after the Lord had ſpoken unto them, he was received up into heaven, and ſate on the right hand of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>HOw well the throne</l>
               <l>Becomes <hi>God's holy One!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How fit the Rod</l>
               <l>Beſeems the hand of God!</l>
               <l>How meet the Crown</l>
               <l>Befits <hi>him!</hi> 't is his own.</l>
               <l>How well, meet, fit, his Throne, Rod, Diadem,</l>
               <l>Deck <hi>him</hi> with glory; but <hi>he</hi> much more <hi>them.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>We wiſh <hi>Good luck</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>thee</hi> with theſe: go pluck</l>
               <l>Hell by the root;</l>
               <l>Make <hi>it</hi> quake at thy foot:</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170697:32"/>
               <l>To right thy Spouſe,</l>
               <l>Damn Death t' a <hi>Charnel-houſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Good luck have with thy right.</hi> Oh how we bleſs</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>thy Father,</hi> for <hi>thy</hi> good ſucceſs!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>With how ſweet bliſs</l>
               <l>Do Grace and Glory kiſs!</l>
               <l>So Light and Heat</l>
               <l>We ſee in <hi>Phoebus</hi> met.</l>
               <l>By theſe 't is known</l>
               <l>Thou not uſurpſt thine own.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Good luck have with thy right:</hi> we willingly</l>
               <l>Submit unto thy yoke of Liberty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>We, if we might,</l>
               <l>Would not ſupplant thy right;</l>
               <l>But yeeld as well,</l>
               <l>As if nor heav'n nor hell</l>
               <l>Should crown or damn</l>
               <l>With endleſs bliſs or ſhame.</l>
               <l>Our <hi>better Natures</hi> will this juſt embrace;</l>
               <l>Nor can we other by <hi>inſtinct of Grace.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Satan,</hi> as heir,</l>
               <l>Long kept his <hi>ſteely</hi> Chair;</l>
               <l>Nay, yet uſurps</l>
               <l>The unregen'rate corps:</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170697:33"/>
               <l>But when Chriſt claim'd</l>
               <l>His right, how was all maim'd?</l>
               <l>Our bleſſed <hi>Gyant having run his courſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now on the heavens rides, as on a horſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>On man 's agreeing</l>
               <l>With Hell, ſin had its being;</l>
               <l>And by this blot,</l>
               <l>Death had her eſſence got.</l>
               <l>Should <hi>Chriſt</hi> theſe things</l>
               <l>Suffer as <hi>fellow-Kings?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No, if they ſtir in us while here we breath,</l>
               <l>They 're the laſt pangs but of a dying Death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>But how large Scenes</l>
               <l>Hath this <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s act? What means</l>
               <l>He to prorogue</l>
               <l>His wiſhed <hi>Epilogue?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And not concludes</l>
               <l>Without more <hi>Interludes?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is not th' earths harveſt ripe?</hi> hath it ſo dull</l>
               <l>In ſinning been? <hi>yet are the Fats not full?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Hell, Sin, and Death,</l>
               <l>Which yet too ſtrongly breath,</l>
               <l>Seem to blaſpheme,</l>
               <l>As if they were <hi>Supreme,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170697:33"/>
               <l>Or their pow'r here,</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Interregnum</hi> were.</l>
               <l>Lord, 'tis long ſince, long, ſince thy promiſe ſpake,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſe days I'll ſhorten, for my choſen's ſake.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On Chriſt's Interceſſion with the Father for us.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Heb. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="25">25 Wherefore he is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt, that come unto God by him; ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>NOr is our <hi>Saviour</hi> ſo much given</l>
               <l>Unto the <hi>contemplation of himſelf,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>he</hi> forgets us now in heaven,</l>
               <l>As, once, prophanely thought <hi>that glutton elf:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But having travers'd hence <hi>his</hi> journey,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> ſtill remembers us amidſt <hi>his</hi> glory;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> ſtill remains our bleſt <hi>Attorney,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170697:34"/>
               <l>Whereof the leaſt act, on our true repentance,</l>
               <l>Is able to reverſe the ſtrongeſt ſentence.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Hence, then, let 's Fortune fear, nor Fate,</l>
               <l>Or what blear-ey'd <hi>Star-gazers</hi> can rehearſe;</l>
               <l>Becauſe we have an <hi>Advocate,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who can each <hi>ominous preſage</hi> reverſe.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Satan</hi> never hence appeal</l>
               <l>To heaven, in his wonted <hi>Dialect,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Leſt he be doom'd by <hi>Chriſt</hi> his zeal,</l>
               <l>As who would make his Death of none effect;</l>
               <l>And aim'd to hinder him, leſt he inherit</l>
               <l>The dear-bought purchaſe which his death did merit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>But if he dare us to attaint,</l>
               <l>He'll ſtrait be ſilenc'd at <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s counter-ſuit,</l>
               <l>As daring to accuſe a Saint</l>
               <l>To whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> will his righteouſneſs impute.</l>
               <l>You then, whoſe troubled ſouls do languiſh</l>
               <l>In pining ſorrow for your ſins and follies,</l>
               <l>Baniſh your fears, and calm your anguiſh;</l>
               <l>Exult, and vent your joy in ſprightly vollies:</l>
               <l>Go, ſee <hi>him</hi> with your tears, &amp; leave the tryal</l>
               <l>To <hi>him</hi> alone, whoſe Suit ne'er found denial.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>If <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> took ſo kinde</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A handful but of water from a Peaſant,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170697:34"/>
               <l>Preſent thy tears, and thou ſhalt finde</l>
               <l>More gracious acceptance of that preſent.</l>
               <l>And if thy ſins ſo thick ſhould croud,</l>
               <l>To fill heav'ns ears with a condemning matter,</l>
               <l>And ſtand between you like a cloud,</l>
               <l>Which not the windes of all thy ſighs can ſcatter;</l>
               <l>By him that ſable cloud ſhall be diſſolv'd,</l>
               <l>Wherein the <hi>Sun of glory</hi> ſeem'd involv'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>In vain let <hi>Satan</hi> henceforth wander,</l>
               <l>Like to a baſe accuſing <hi>Ottacus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As daring to inform by ſlander</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him that's all ear and eye,</hi> concerning us:</l>
               <l>Thus let us then foreſtal his malice;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Accuſe our ſelves;</hi> let not that ſeem uncouth:</l>
               <l>Who will not ſo; with Juſtice dallies:</l>
               <l>But ſo we do his office, ſtop his mouth.</l>
               <l>Our Caſe thus op'ned, if <hi>Chriſt</hi> intercede,</l>
               <l>What envious boldneſs dares againſt us plead?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>What means that <hi>Man of ſin,</hi> that rallies</l>
               <l>The <hi>Saints</hi> as <hi>Chriſt's corrivals</hi> in this <hi>Function?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And if they were ſo neer his <hi>allies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How was it purchaſed? when was their Unction?</l>
               <l>True, with him are the <hi>Saints</hi> co-heirs;</l>
               <l>But <hi>Chriſt</hi> did purchaſe it, and them elected:</l>
               <l>And they to whom now <hi>Rome</hi> repairs,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Saints,</hi> now by <hi>him</hi> reign, ſo here expected.</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170697:35"/>
               <l>He is our <hi>elder Brother,</hi> and he ſure</l>
               <l>Enjoys his right of primogeniture.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Then have our hands tranſgreſs'd the warrant</l>
               <l>Of heav'ns Laws? <hi>Chriſt pleads his hands bor'd through:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or have our devious feet been errant?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> pleads <hi>his pierc'd,</hi> by a ſufficient proof.</l>
               <l>Or if our hearts have Ill invented,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> pleads <hi>his</hi> for us by the Souldier pierc'd;</l>
               <l>All was on <hi>him</hi> by ſtripes indented:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> ſues the Fine of all on him amerc'd.</l>
               <l>In <hi>him</hi> our ſins were ſcourg'd, bor'd, nail'd, and rack'd;</l>
               <l>Nor will <hi>his Father</hi> them again exact.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Our ſins but whiſper to that cry</l>
               <l>Which <hi>his</hi> wounds make; the ſorrow &amp; compunction</l>
               <l>Of <hi>his</hi> perplexed Agony;</l>
               <l>Nay, with our ſins if hell howl'd in conjunction.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our thanks</hi> he <hi>graciouſly perfumes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our ſupplications with odours balms;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sweetens with myrrhe repentant rheums;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With incenſe ſanctifies our vows and alms.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Bleſt be <hi>thy Father,</hi> and that ſacred Unction.</l>
               <l>That did conſigne <hi>thee</hi> to this bleſſed Function.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170697:35"/>
            <head>On Chriſt his final coming to Judgment.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Revel. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="12">12 And the Sun became black as ſackcloth of hair, and the moon became as blood.</p>
                  <p n="13">13 And the ſtars of heaven fell unto the earth, even as a fig-tree casteth her untimely figs, when ſhe is ſhaken of a mighty winde.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 And the heaven departed as a ſeroll when it is rolled together, and every mountain and iſland were moved out of their places.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>NOr here our <hi>Saviour</hi> concludes</l>
               <l>His act: theſe are <hi>his Interludes:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The eye of faith in theſe <hi>he</hi> asks,</l>
               <l>As being an <hi>Interview</hi> of Masks.</l>
               <l>But he upon a <hi>flaming ſtage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In an <hi>Angelick equipage;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now comes in perſon at the day of Audit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When <hi>troops of angels ſhall trump forth his plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170697:36"/>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>When righteouſneſs and equitie</l>
               <l>The pillars of his Seat ſhall be;</l>
               <l>The elements together mixt,</l>
               <l>And the two Poles of th' world unfixt:</l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>Genius</hi> ſhall feel that ſtory</l>
               <l>Of the imagin'd <hi>Purgatory,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When wild Diſorder, and amaz'd Confuſion,</l>
               <l>Shall be the Whifflers to a ſad concluſion?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>But, Lord, how long wilt thou defer</l>
               <l>To hear! Wilt ſtill our hopes deter?</l>
               <l>How long that <hi>Quaere</hi> wilt ſuſpend,</l>
               <l>Whether the world ſhall have an end?</l>
               <l>Come, let thy judgement and thy mercy</l>
               <l>Finiſh at length that Controverſie.</l>
               <l>Come, come away, our panting hearts are drumming</l>
               <l>At thy approach, and yet thou ſeem'ſt not coming.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Haſte, Lord, deſcend, thy Saints to <hi>gather,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And to reſigne them to thy Father.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What wilt thou loſe by that thy tender?</l>
               <l>'Tis no ſurpriſal or ſurrender:</l>
               <l>Thou 'lt be the <hi>King of glory</hi> ſtill.</l>
               <l>For who dares to oppoſe thy will?</l>
               <l>Safe in <hi>thy Eden</hi> grows the <hi>tree of life:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou now not doubtſt of <hi>Adam</hi> or his wife.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170697:36"/>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>But ſtay, my ſoul; what, canſt thou meet</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Judge</hi> with clean prepared feet?</l>
               <l>Art thou not naked, or art cloth'd</l>
               <l>As one to ſuch a Lord betroth'd?</l>
               <l>If ſo, go meet thy coming Groom;</l>
               <l>Thy wedding-day's the day of Doom.</l>
               <l>But, Lord, we build, wed, feaſt; we vaunt and jet,</l>
               <l>As 't were but now thou ſaidſt, <hi>But th'end's not yet.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>As morning-light precedes the Sun,</l>
               <l>Let grace thy glory here fore-run:</l>
               <l>For glory never there will come,</l>
               <l>Where grace hath not prepar'd the room.</l>
               <l>Give grace, Lord, and, with that, the ſinew</l>
               <l>Of ſtrength and vigour to continue.</l>
               <l>Thou haſt been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and begun to do;</l>
               <l>But ſeem'ſt <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> too.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>O let not Hell upbraid thy power,</l>
               <l>As <hi>his</hi> that <hi>'gan to build that tower</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He could not end.</hi> Finiſh at length</l>
               <l>My <hi>Citadel</hi> with mighty ſtrength.</l>
               <l>Yet, faith and hope faint; joys are ſory,</l>
               <l>Till grace be ſwallow'd up of glory.</l>
               <l>As grace, like <hi>Orphah,</hi> leaves me when I die;</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Ruth</hi>-like glory fill my <hi>Naomi.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170697:37"/>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Bleſt God, I know we ought to pray,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy kingdom come,</hi> each day by day;</l>
               <l>And ſhould thy coming damn us all,</l>
               <l>We durſt but it a mercy call.</l>
               <l>Thy time, dread Lord, 's the beſt; and thou</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Long-ſuff'ring</hi> art, of old and now.</l>
               <l>O let thy grace make way for glory; then</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy kingdom come, thy will be done.</hi> Amen.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the Joys of heaven after the day of Judgment.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Cor. 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="9">9 Eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have entred into the heart of man, the things which God hath prepared for them that love him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>GHeſs now the Scenes of ev'ry age</l>
               <l>Upon one Stage</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170697:37"/>
               <l>Re-acted, and all ſhifted clean,</l>
               <l>Both Stage and Scene;</l>
               <l>Each hath his pay, and wafted home,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Go</hi> or <hi>Come;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To act a better part, or worſe,</l>
               <l>With bliſs or curſe.</l>
               <l>Both play'd have to my Fancies eye,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Tragi-Comi-Comi-Tragedy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>As heav'n <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> confines</l>
               <l>To <hi>Zones</hi> and <hi>Lines;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And with conceited <hi>Poles</hi> ſupports</l>
               <l>The azure Courts;</l>
               <l>And th'row its fancied <hi>Zodiack,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can <hi>Titan</hi> track;</l>
               <l>And takes heav'ns length and breadth, if bid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As th' Angel did:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Their <hi>Jacob's ſtaff</hi> no leſs can do</l>
               <l>Then if they had got <hi>Jacob's ladder too.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Yet all this ſerves but to advance</l>
               <l>Gilt <hi>Ignorance:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So heav'ns joys by blinde devotions</l>
               <l>Are cloath'd in notions,</l>
               <l>Which onely gild our <hi>Neſcience</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With ſeeming ſence.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Them</hi> we are forc'd to gheſs by pleaſures,</l>
               <l>And earthly treaſures:</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170697:38"/>
               <l>Since though the <hi>Turkiſh Alcharon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deſcribes their <hi>Par'diſe,</hi> ours can be by none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>But could our <hi>Merlins,</hi> by diſcerning</l>
               <l>And <hi>Lynx</hi>-ey'd learning,</l>
               <l>Who can the ſtarry <hi>Alphabet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In language ſet;</l>
               <l>And though the clouds ſhould blot their book,</l>
               <l>Can th'row them look:</l>
               <l>Could they define the bleſſed manſions</l>
               <l>B'yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d theſe expanſions;</l>
               <l>I'd love their Art: <hi>Divinity</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should then be <hi>handmaid</hi> to <hi>Aſtronomy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>As on their <hi>Babel</hi> of Conceit</l>
               <l>They mount heav'ns height:</l>
               <l>So, though its beauty and dimenſion</l>
               <l>Befools Invention,</l>
               <l>Tranſcends the <hi>Zenith</hi> of all mancie</l>
               <l>Of Art and Fancie;</l>
               <l>Yet ſince <hi>that</hi> faculty of ſoul</l>
               <l>Doth more inroll</l>
               <l>Then 's ſeen or heard, we gheſs thoſe joys,</l>
               <l>Though far above our knowledge, wiſh, or choice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>To call them <hi>Riches,</hi> were not high,</l>
               <l>But beggerly:</l>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170697:38"/>
               <l>To call them <hi>Honours,</hi> were a vile</l>
               <l>Inglorious ſtile:</l>
               <l>To call them <hi>Pleaſures,</hi> were a groſs</l>
               <l>And tedious gloſs,</l>
               <l>Theſe <hi>Joys</hi> by <hi>myriads</hi> of pitches</l>
               <l>Exceed <hi>ſuch Riches:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though by ſuch names the <hi>bleſſed Spirit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deſcribes thoſe joys which now the <hi>Saints</hi> inherit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Since no man th' heavens ever knew,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Art</hi> or view;</l>
               <l>Though ſome the <hi>Stars</hi> boaſt to deſcribe,</l>
               <l>By <hi>name</hi> and tribe:</l>
               <l>As if when firſt the heavens were,</l>
               <l>They had been there,</l>
               <l>And knew them <hi>all</hi> as well as <hi>he,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His ſilver skie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not knowing <hi>theſe,</hi> ſo plain and even,</l>
               <l>Who can define the non-apparent heaven?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Lord, ſince more then I can conceive,</l>
               <l>I muſt believe;</l>
               <l>And far beyond my <hi>Fancies</hi> ſcope,</l>
               <l>I ſtill muſt hope:</l>
               <l>Grant, what's conceived by my youth</l>
               <l>Agree with truth:</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170697:39"/>
               <l>And whatſoever doth out-ſtretch</l>
               <l>My Fancies reach,</l>
               <l>She at <hi>forbidden fruit</hi> not glance,</l>
               <l>But flag her wing in humble <hi>Ignorance.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the Torments of Hell.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Luke 16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="22">22 And it came to paſs that the begger died, and was buried, and was carried by the angels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Abrahams boſom. The rich man alſo died, and was buried.</p>
                  <p n="23">23 And in hell he lift up his eyes, being in tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſees Abraham afar off, and Lazarus in his boſom.</p>
                  <p n="24">24 And he cried, and ſaid, Father Abraham, have mercy on me, and ſend Lazarus that he may dip the tip of his finger in water, and cool my tongue: for I am tormented in this flame.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>POor ſouls! whom endleſs flames do ſcorch,</l>
               <l>Since that the earth flam'd like a <hi>pendant Torch;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170697:39"/>
               <l>Since at the <hi>Trumpets final ſound,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our <hi>Jericho</hi>'s high walls fell flat to ground,</l>
               <l>And all was burnt: What Verſe hath tones</l>
               <l>Sufficient to accent forth your groans?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Should all the <hi>Poets</hi> adde each <hi>Fury,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And of the <hi>Muſes</hi> Nine make up a <hi>Jury,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And beg their Verdict to define</l>
               <l>Hell 's miſeries; they muſt the Suit decline,</l>
               <l>Should they exhauſt their <hi>Helicon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And theſe ſhould drain their <hi>Styx</hi> and <hi>Acharon.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Let Wit excite her fruitleſs ſtrife,</l>
               <l>To limn Eternal Death unto the Life,</l>
               <l>And in a Synod call the <hi>Quire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or <hi>Arts,</hi> all ſerved but to paint a fire;</l>
               <l>Fire which but makes the brain to ſweat,</l>
               <l>As void of true deſcription, as of heat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Reader, let thy <hi>Orpheus-like Fancie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deſcend to Hell in ſome conceited <hi>Maney,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And with brisk <hi>Nectar</hi> oil the mouth</l>
               <l>Of tortur'd <hi>Dives,</hi> which is parch'd with drouth;</l>
               <l>All he could ſay how <hi>Furies</hi> wreak</l>
               <l>Their rage, would be, <hi>I know not what to ſpeak.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aetna</hi>'s to this an idle tapor,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Veſuvius</hi> a thin incenſed vapor;</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170697:40"/>
               <l>Or as the <hi>Pyramids,</hi> whoſe ſpires</l>
               <l>Mount onely in proportion'd ſhapes of fires:</l>
               <l>No fire to theſe is worth a name;</l>
               <l>Even <hi>Sodom</hi>'s but the ſhadow of this flame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>And what need <hi>Poets</hi> feign a <hi>Styx</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or <hi>Acharon,</hi> ſince floods of tears here mix</l>
               <l>Into a Sea, which wildly lurks</l>
               <l>In darkneſs, and confuſed water-works;</l>
               <l>Which all <hi>Hydrography</hi> no better</l>
               <l>Can quote, then <hi>Xerxes</hi> th' <hi>Helleſpont</hi> could fetter.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>But cannot <hi>Dives</hi> from <hi>Theſe</hi> drench</l>
               <l>His thirſt-parch'd mouth, and burning liver quench?</l>
               <l>No: fire and water here are both</l>
               <l>One element, which flaming ſtreams do froth:</l>
               <l>Both having purg'd the world ſo groſs,</l>
               <l>Meet in Hell 's furnace, to conſume the droſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Lord ſince Hell 's pains exceed conceit,</l>
               <l>Each gloſs on them 's a naked counterfeit:</l>
               <l>Our Fancies ſtill have ſome remorſe;</l>
               <l>Let us the worſt imagine, ſtill 't is worſe.</l>
               <l>If heavens joys can't draw me home,</l>
               <l>Let theſe true terrors fright me till I come.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170697:40"/>
            <head>The ſecond Part. On ſeveral occaſions, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral texts of Scripture.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 119.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="37">37 O turn away mine eyes, leſt they behold vanity.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>LOrd, what 's a Beauty! but a paint, at moſt,</l>
               <l>Which with a breath's gone, 't is ſo vainly gloſt.</l>
               <l>What beauty's dy'd ſo deep in grain, that dolour,</l>
               <l>Or age, or ſickneſs, cannot blaſt its colour?</l>
               <l>Since there's within 't no principle to nouriſh</l>
               <l>Its verdant vigour to a conſtant flouriſh,</l>
               <l>Lord, let me think 't but a more ſpecious worm,</l>
               <l>And wink its beauty to an <hi>Antick</hi> form.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170697:41"/>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Lord, what's a beauty! in it could I ſee</l>
               <l>The <hi>Image</hi> which I loſt in loſing thee,</l>
               <l>I'd court, and gaze, till through mine eyes that face</l>
               <l>Reprinted on my ſoul that former grace.</l>
               <l>Here's no ſuch form: although indeed ſome few</l>
               <l>Think that in it we may <hi>thy footſteps view.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What's beauty then, for which we ſo much brawl,</l>
               <l>But fleſh tranſparent th'row a ſmoother cawl?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Lord, what's a Beauty? Did a more divine</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Saint</hi> dwell within't, I would adore the ſhrine;</l>
               <l>My captiv'd heart with zealous love ſhould boil;</l>
               <l>I'd count each beauty as this beauty's foil.</l>
               <l>But ſince the ſoul, the better part, is tainted,</l>
               <l>Can th' outward part be free? muſt that be Sainted?</l>
               <l>What's beauty then, if it be void of grace?</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Philip's Blackmore</hi> had the fairer face.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Lord, what's a Beauty! our fair <hi>Grannam Eve</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Soon prov'd a ſtrong <hi>Suadela,</hi> to deceive.</l>
               <l>This treach'rous <hi>White &amp; Red</hi> hath bred more war,</l>
               <l>Then they did once 'twixt <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lord, let me think thoſe eyes by th' wanton Muſe</l>
               <l>Stil'd Stars, are <hi>Ignes fatui,</hi> to ſeduce:</l>
               <l>Thoſe Coral-lips, my credit would explode;</l>
               <l>Theſe Yv'ry teeth, my good report corrode.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170697:41"/>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>Lord, what's the world! Thou didſt not mean, I gheſs,</l>
               <l>Th'worlds for Impoſtures, either great or leſs;</l>
               <l>Nor mean'ſt the leſſer, whom thou mad'ſt complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</l>
               <l>Should be at all ſeduced by the greater.</l>
               <l>Yet as they repreſent each others parts,</l>
               <l>The greater too hath its deluſive Arts.</l>
               <l>Since then they're objects both to tempt mine eyes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O turn them from beholding vanities.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Lord, what's the world? 't is but a turning Globe,</l>
               <l>Which whirls us now on high, then lowe as <hi>Job;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or a toſs'd ſhip, whoſe now-aſpiring Maſt</l>
               <l>Seems for to boar the clouds, then back doth caſt</l>
               <l>Her rolling paſſengers, to ſeek a Tomb</l>
               <l>In ſome vaſt Sea-ſhell, or ſome fiſhes womb.</l>
               <l>Then what's the world? a bubble 'tis at moſt;</l>
               <l>With winde 'tis onely full, with winde 'tis toſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Lord, what's the world? I will not wiſh me blinde,</l>
               <l>Becauſe mine eyes thus tempt me; though I finde</l>
               <l>A grave
<note n="*" place="margin">Bp. <hi>Hall.</hi>
                  </note> one bid one, of one eye bereft,</l>
               <l>Not t' weep that loſs, but that one yet was left:</l>
               <l>Nor will miſtake thee, when thou bidſt not doubt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If that mine eye offend, to pluck it out.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lord, turn away mine eyes: all's one to me,</l>
               <l>If ſo thou doſt, as if I did not ſee.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170697:42"/>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Lord, what's the world? indeed the heav'ns aray'd</l>
               <l>Are in thy Livery; we ſee diſplay'd</l>
               <l>In them thy <hi>glorious Coat;</hi> they each night ſtory</l>
               <l>In <hi>Starry characters</hi> their <hi>Makers</hi> glory.</l>
               <l>But ſince a fly, worm, or the meaneſt elf,</l>
               <l>If animate, excels the world it ſelf;</l>
               <l>Why then's the world by noble man thus held</l>
               <l>In ſuch eſteem, that is by ſuch excell'd?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>The Author's <hi>Epainicron</hi> to God, for his Recovery from a ſharp Fever.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 118.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="18">18 The Lord hath chaſtened and corrected me ſore: but he hath not given me over unto death.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſai. 38.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="18">18 For the grave cannot praiſe thee; death cannot celebrate thee: they that go down to the pit, canner hope for thy truth.</p>
                  <p n="19">19. The living the living he ſhall praiſe thee, as I do this day.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170697:42"/>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord,</hi> THough Scripture ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A thouſand yeers one day</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are unto thee;</hi> yet muſt I think again,</l>
               <l>To thee appears</l>
               <l>Each day a thouſand yeers,</l>
               <l>Till I thee thank for freedom from my pain.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Late I was ſick;</l>
               <l>'Twere vain with Launcet's prick</l>
               <l>To vent my blood corrupted too too long:</l>
               <l>I look'd for death,</l>
               <l>As he that lay beneath</l>
               <l>A threatning ſword which by a thred was hung.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>The active ſtrife</l>
               <l>For hope or help of life,</l>
               <l>Now fail'd me quite. And while the Doctor lingers,</l>
               <l>How did I feel</l>
               <l>A haſtie Death to ceel</l>
               <l>My falling eye-lids with her Ycie fingers?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>The quick reſults</l>
               <l>Within my fev'riſh Pulſe,</l>
               <l>The minutes were by which the hours I counted;</l>
               <l>Wherein delay'd</l>
               <l>The tarder Doctors ayd:</l>
               <l>So hours to days, and days to weeks amounted.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170697:43"/>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>To hold me home,</l>
               <l>My laſt <hi>Viaticum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was tender'd, to ſuſtain me in my journey:</l>
               <l>Nor was I mute</l>
               <l>For to preſent my ſute</l>
               <l>To th' mediation of my <hi>ſweet Attorney.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Life's influence,</l>
               <l>Scar'd from my outward ſence,</l>
               <l>Now to my hearts <hi>Metropolis</hi> was gone;</l>
               <l>And in this ſtrait,</l>
               <l>My ready ſoul did wait</l>
               <l>With nimble wing for diſſolution.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>But like a <hi>brand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pluck'd by thy gracious hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I have eſcap'd the burning unconſum'd:</l>
               <l>Though death by Fever</l>
               <l>Did rage as bad as ever.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Caldee</hi>'s King on the <hi>furnac'd children</hi> fum'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>But as they, freed,</l>
               <l>With one conſent agreed</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To praiſe thee for thy kindneſs and thy love:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So let me praiſe</l>
               <l>Thy mercy all my days;</l>
               <l>So ſhall this mercy not my judgement prove.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170697:43"/>
            <head>Temptation.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſ. 6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="14">14 Stand faſt therefore, having your loyns girt about with truth, and having on the breſt-plate of righteouſneſs,</p>
                  <p n="15">15 And your feet ſhed with the preparation of the Goſpel of peace.</p>
                  <p n="16">16 Above all, taking the ſhield of faith, whereby ye ſhall be able to quench all the fiery darts of the wicked.</p>
                  <p n="17">17 And take the helmet of ſalvation, and the ſword of the Spirit, which is the word of God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>NOr was with Death my combat ſuch,</l>
               <l>But now I'm tempted all ſo much;</l>
               <l>So that me thinks my Senſes halt</l>
               <l>'Twixt two; which was the worſt aſſault:</l>
               <l>Unleſs thou, Lord, who conquer'dſt Death,</l>
               <l>And lately crown'dſt me with that wreath;</l>
               <l>As thou haſt vanquiſh'd Hell too, I'm undone,</l>
               <l>Unleſs thou finiſh what thou haſt begun.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170697:44"/>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Is't not enough, by the ſiniſter</l>
               <l>Temptations of her <hi>whiſp'ring ſiſter</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My ſoul's ſeduc'd, with frailty cloath'd;</l>
               <l>And to infirmity betroth'd;</l>
               <l>That th'eaſie ſoul by fleſh is tempted,</l>
               <l>Nor night, nor day, nor place exempted;</l>
               <l>As if in ſlights ſhe did the Devil ape,</l>
               <l>And meant them no temptations, but a rape?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Is't not enough, that by the fraud</l>
               <l>of Hell, that makes the World her <hi>Band,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'm by the World ſeduc'd; and Senſe</l>
               <l>Wooes, not refiſts its influence;</l>
               <l>Whoſe very bleſſings are but Baits,</l>
               <l>As if th' air breath'd nought but deceits:</l>
               <l>So that we all might breathe our mourning thus;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Falſe world, Impoſture is thy Genius?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>But are we ſubject to the darts</l>
               <l>Of helliſh Fiends, which ſeize our hearts,</l>
               <l>Like ſubtil Lightning's fierce inqueſts,</l>
               <l>Which melts the gold within the cheſts?</l>
               <l>As if they aim'd t'uſurp thy part,</l>
               <l>Who onely know'ſt and try'ſt the heart;</l>
               <l>Into whoſe Cloſets they themſelves convey,</l>
               <l>Unleſs thou, Lord, vouchſafe to keep the key.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170697:44"/>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, gird my loyns with truth, and dreſs</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me i'th'breſt-plate of righteouſneſs;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let my feet be prepar'd,</hi> (my God)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And with the peaceful Goſpel ſhod:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shield me with faith,</hi> (the chiefeſt Spell)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To quench the firy darts of hell:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Daign th'helmet of ſalvation, and the ſword</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of thy bleſt Spirit,</hi> Lord, <hi>which is thy Word.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>But I no more can wear this armour,</l>
               <l>Then thy Delight and <hi>Judah's Par'mour</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Could ſtout <hi>Saul</hi>'s againſt <hi>him</hi> of <hi>Gath;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For ſuch too are <hi>Hell</hi>'s arms and wrath:</l>
               <l>Nor can no more foyl with thy Word,</l>
               <l>Then could that <hi>Turk</hi> with <hi>Caſtriot</hi>'s ſword:</l>
               <l>I'm weak and ignorant; 't is thou alone</l>
               <l>Muſt teach me both to fight, and put it on.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>But where's this Armour to be found?</l>
               <l>No <hi>Cyclops</hi> frame it under ground.</l>
               <l>He hopes in vain to win the field,</l>
               <l>Who fights againſt Hell with Hell's ſhield:</l>
               <l>Such Armours are but empty ſhrouds,</l>
               <l>As thin and airy as the clouds.</l>
               <l>Thou, who wilt crown our conqueſt, doſt impale</l>
               <l>Our ſouls with theſe Arms, from thy <hi>Arſenal.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170697:45"/>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Then if thou ſtor'ſt me with theſe Arms,</l>
               <l>My ſoul ſhall need no other Charms;</l>
               <l>If thou with theſe my ſpirit furniſh,</l>
               <l>They'll fright Hell with their very burniſh;</l>
               <l>Nor doubt I leſt Hells arrows points</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Should wound me th'row theſe armors joints:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I then might ſend that anſwer, <hi>Let him ſcoff,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And boaſt at laſt, that puts his armour off.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 62.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="9">9 As for the children of men, they are but vain; the children of men are deceitful upon the weights: they are altogether lighter then vanity it ſelf.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>DRead Lord! w'are all too light: the empty ſcale</l>
               <l>Towards heav'n mounts with a complaining tale:</l>
               <l>The over-balanc'd one on <hi>Orcus</hi> knocks,</l>
               <l>As if it means to rend the brazen locks</l>
               <l>That priſon vengeance; and it preſſeth deep,</l>
               <l>As if it thought Deſtruction were aſleep.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170697:45"/>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>If thus our Caſe with dreadful Juſtice ſtand,</l>
               <l>How ſhall we ſcape her tother armed hand?</l>
               <l>Think we God is not with our ways acquainted,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Juſtice</hi>'s Sword no ſharper then 't is painted?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Lion's painted fiercer then he is:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But deeming <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſo, we judge amiſs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Thus ſtands our Caſe: but if thy Mercy buoys</l>
               <l>Th' o'er-balanc'd Scale in even counterpoize,</l>
               <l>Then may we paſs good, with a grain or two</l>
               <l>Of thy dear blood, as oft light Pieces do:</l>
               <l>And then if <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſhould be moſt extreme,</l>
               <l>We ſhould o'er-weigh with a declining beam.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>But ſince Sin's heavie too, how can agree</l>
               <l>In truth this various <hi>levi-gravity?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Unleſs it be, that weighty things we fleight,</l>
               <l>And over-value things of ſlender weight.</l>
               <l>Thus Scriptures juſtly their complaints may levy:</l>
               <l>In weighty things w'are light, in light things heavy</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>But ſhouldſt thou weigh us as w'are in our ſelves,</l>
               <l>Vain as Inconſtancie, and light as Elves;</l>
               <l>Mightſt thou not by the breath of thy diſpleaſure,</l>
               <l>Breath into nought at all our empty meaſure?</l>
               <l>And mightſt <hi>Belſhazzar</hi>'s doom with that ſame hand,</l>
               <l>Not onely on our walls, but foreheads brand?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170697:46"/>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Dread Lord, the beſt are <hi>as the ſmalled duſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Within the balance:</hi> ſo thy Truth diſcuſt:</l>
               <l>How can we then expect but to miſcarry,</l>
               <l>Weigh'd with the <hi>Shekel of thy Sanctuary?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such, angry <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſoon to hell proſcribes,</l>
               <l>Who hath quick eyes to judg, tho' none for bribes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>If could our Churls with Gold, our airy Gallants,</l>
               <l>With all their Glories, raiſe the ſtooping balance;</l>
               <l>In ſheets of Gold I'd clothe me; never check</l>
               <l>At Honours Lure, but ſtill obey its beck:</l>
               <l>But Gold is vain, and Honour light; and they,</l>
               <l>The more they're lin'd with theſe, the leſs they weigh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Thus ſhouldſt thou weigh what man amiſs hath don,</l>
               <l>What man could ſtand it, but thy <hi>onely Son?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who was weigh'd in man's balance of deceit,</l>
               <l>That we might be found of ſufficient weight;</l>
               <l>Who was out-weigh'd by <hi>thirty pence,</hi> that we</l>
               <l>Might ſo paſs currant in thy <hi>Treaſury.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170697:46"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eccleſ. 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="11">11 When goods increaſe, they are increaſed that eat them: and what good is there to the owners thereof, ſaving the beholding of them with their eyes?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <l>GO, Worldings, ſet your eye-lids on the rack;</l>
               <l>Gaze on your wealth, until your eye-ſtrings crack.</l>
               <l>With too intenſive views, all your delight</l>
               <l>May weary, but ne'er ſatisfie your ſight;</l>
               <l>No, though the windows of your eyes were glaz'd</l>
               <l>With Multiplying-glaſſes while you gaz'd.</l>
               <l>You that adore your heaps with admiration,</l>
               <l>As doth <hi>Aſtronomy a Conſtellation;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And if with th' heav'ns you in love do joyn,</l>
               <l>'Tis 'cauſe they're of the colour with your Coyn:</l>
               <l>Go hug your ſelves in your belov'd condition;</l>
               <l>You onely have in <hi>uſe,</hi> I in <hi>fruition</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe gifts of Fortune: Vertue may indeed</l>
               <l>Them be without; but you do ſtand in need</l>
               <l>Amidſt your wealth; neither can you boaſt more</l>
               <l>Of being rich, then I of being poor.</l>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170697:47"/>
               <l>Now can my ſoul mount freely with her wings,</l>
               <l>Not with the baggage clog'd of earthly things.</l>
               <l>Here parents may, by underſerv'd removes,</l>
               <l>Deveſt us of our birth-right, and their loves:</l>
               <l>So that all duty can't induce their minde,</l>
               <l>No, not to ſhare their ſtore by <hi>Gavel-kinde;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So leaving grief and poverty their portion,</l>
               <l>As if their firſt-born were but an abortion.</l>
               <l>There <hi>Satan</hi>'s Vouchers can nor diſ-inherit,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Juſtice</hi> cauſe divorce, where <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s my merit.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As falſe, as ſad, is that concluſion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That thinks Gods bleſſing's with a birth-right gone.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Come, worldlings, come, who wiſh to have no pledge</l>
               <l>Of your ſalvation, but <hi>Achan</hi>'s wedge;</l>
               <l>I'll ſhew you wealth, to which your gold is droſs,</l>
               <l>And all your Gallants bravery but moſs.</l>
               <l>Within you glorious curtains thou mayſt finde</l>
               <l>A Carkanet of Jewels is enſhrin'd.</l>
               <l>Aſcend, and tell me if a Pearl ere ſhone</l>
               <l>In equal luſtre with you <hi>Jaſper-ſtone.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Jewels of a <hi>Monarch</hi>'s Crown, the coſt</l>
               <l>Wherewith of old were <hi>Aaron</hi>'s Robes imboſt,</l>
               <l>Were childiſh ſhells to theſe, true <hi>Midas</hi> diſhes,</l>
               <l>Which do but choak the owner with his wiſhes.</l>
               <l>There's the true <hi>Topaz, Iacinth,</hi> and <hi>Beryl;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What Jewel not? which thou without the peril</l>
               <l>Of <hi>coveting</hi> mayſt luſt for: there's a <hi>Mine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which onely if thou wilt deſire, is thine.</l>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170697:47"/>
               <l>'Tis not <hi>Idolatry</hi> to be thus greedy,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Piety: thrice-bleſſed are ſuch needy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why doſt thou ſtartle at this wealthy tender,</l>
               <l>Which Thieves can't rob, nor Fortune cauſe ſurrender?</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="13">13. He that covereth his ſin, ſhall not prosper.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>COver our ſins!</l>
               <l>Sees not bright <hi>Phoſper</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Falſe <hi>Weights</hi> and <hi>Hins;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And can they proſper?</l>
               <l>Sin may, like a falſe <hi>Nun,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cloyſter'd in darkneſs lie:</l>
               <l>It may avoid the Sun,</l>
               <l>Not God's revenging eye.</l>
               <l>Some, yet, to cloathe their naked ſin,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Eve</hi> and <hi>Adam</hi> ſowe fig-leaves;</l>
               <l>And one to hide his Vices in,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such webs as doth the Spider, weaves.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But if could fooliſh ſin avail to cover</l>
               <l>The skies with theſe imaginary clouds;</l>
               <l>Would not a quick-ey'd pendant veng'ance hover,</l>
               <l>To rend and pierce their artificial ſhrouds?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170697:48"/>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Cover our ſins</l>
               <l>From God? From him</l>
               <l>What wings or fins</l>
               <l>Can flie or ſwim?</l>
               <l>We <hi>Wizards</hi> need, nor <hi>Weirds,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No torturing extremes:</l>
               <l>Truths Vouchers, flocks or herds,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>walls will be, or beams.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What Medium's ſo groſs, t' exclude</l>
               <l>God, who's all, whe'er in earth or skie?</l>
               <l>Who's in ſo cloſe a Parlour mew'd,</l>
               <l>To ſhun his ſight, who is all eye?</l>
               <l>What darkneſs, but the God of light can ſcatter?</l>
               <l>His ſearching <hi>winde</hi> doth enter ev'ry cranny.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Juſtice</hi> puts off her Vizor, though ſome flatter,</l>
               <l>'Tis at wilde aim if that her ſword ſmite any.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Cover our ſins!</l>
               <l>Since puniſhment</l>
               <l>And vice are twins,</l>
               <l>Though different.</l>
               <l>Wrath takes ſin by the heel,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Jacob Eſau</hi> once;</l>
               <l>And makes it fall or kneel</l>
               <l>T'hell, or repentant groans.</l>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170697:48"/>
               <l>No eager hoof, or flipp'ry keel,</l>
               <l>Can ſin to ſafe <hi>Aſylums</hi> bear;</l>
               <l>Though hid within a winding eel,</l>
               <l>Or in evaſions couch'd it were.</l>
               <l>Let's not in private dare an evil fact,</l>
               <l>Leſt with a <hi>Cockatrices</hi> killing eye,</l>
               <l>God make his Seeing and Revenge one act:</l>
               <l>No time or place knew long immunity.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Cover our ſins!</l>
               <l>Sees <hi>Iſr'el</hi>'s keeper</l>
               <l>Onely the skin,</l>
               <l>And ſees no deeper?</l>
               <l>Ere done, he ſees our deeds;</l>
               <l>Much more when they are done:</l>
               <l>He ſees them in their ſeeds;</l>
               <l>Much more when they are grown.</l>
               <l>If we could hide us in the air,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heav'n is God's molten Looking-glaſs:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should we for ſafety t' hell repair,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Holl hath nor covering nor caſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But if we ſo much luſt to lurk and hide,</l>
               <l>Let's take <hi>Aſylum in thoſe bleſt five clifts</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of that great Rock;</hi> let's neſtle in his ſide:</l>
               <l>Let us his <hi>Prieſthood</hi> feed upon theſe <hi>fifts.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170697:49"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 60.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="2">2 Thou haſt moved the land, and divided it: heal the ſores thereof, for it ſhaketh.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>TH'aſt mov'd us, Lord; our troubled times reſemble</l>
               <l>An earth-quake beſt; for ſo we quake &amp; tremble.</l>
               <l>The lofty fabricks of our beauteous <hi>Iſles</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now lie confus'd, and heap'd in ru'nous piles.</l>
               <l>Lord, thou haſt mov'd us, as <hi>corn-fields we finde</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Decline their knotty ſtems before the winde.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Yet thou canſt move worſe then by Civil wars;</l>
               <l>When thou ſhalt move the world, when <hi>fixed ſtars</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like Autumn-leaves ſhall from the heavens drop,</l>
               <l>When the feign'd <hi>Poles</hi> ſhall fail to under-prop</l>
               <l>Their maſſie weight: yet Lord, now, let thy love</l>
               <l>And mercy move us, ere thy pow'r thus move.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170697:49"/>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Lord, thou haſt mov'd our land; it moved hath</l>
               <l>Been by the breath of thy provoked wrath,</l>
               <l>Worſe then that wind that would diſpeople th'woods,</l>
               <l>And make proud Maſts to kiſs the angry floods:</l>
               <l>Yet ſince thy breath can kindle coals worſe far</l>
               <l>Then thoſe of <hi>Juniper,</hi> untouch'd we are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Our land's a broken bone, by Diſcord burſt;</l>
               <l>Which timely ſet, may prove as ſtrong as firſt;</l>
               <l>But if delay'd until a Gangrene ſeize it,</l>
               <l>What art can cure it, or what hand can eaſe it?</l>
               <l>When man's help fails, thou only canſt complete it:</l>
               <l>None but thy hand, that broke the bone, can ſet it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>W' are ſick; no part in or 'twixt th' head or foot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But is diſe as'd, ſick both in branch and root:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But ſince moſt Doctors, while they cure, exhauſt</l>
               <l>The moiſture radical, and ſpirits waſt;</l>
               <l>Let's unto him, whoſe wiſdom knows at length</l>
               <l>To cure the wound, yet not t' impair the ſtrength.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>My heart bleeds, Lord, to think our <hi>Nation hath</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So few to ſtand betwixt us and thy wrath:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our fins ſo hainous might moſt juſtly <hi>ſhame</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The mouth of Mercy for to plead our name;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſeems to plead, at <hi>Mercy</hi> vext,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bold Mercy ceaſe thy chat, my turn is next.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170697:50"/>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>How groſs is Nature's ſin, that thus can move,</l>
               <l>As here on earth, ſo war in heav'n above?</l>
               <l>Sets God againſt himſelf, can raiſe diſputes</l>
               <l>Betwixt his juſt and gracious Attributes.</l>
               <l>Will not the angry heav'ns the world impeach</l>
               <l>As true occaſioners of this their breach?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>But <hi>thou,</hi> who both in one haſt reconcil'd,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Mercy</hi> ſate content, ſtern <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſmil'd;</l>
               <l>On thee the weight of all our ſins was laid:</l>
               <l>Oh do not us again with them upbraid.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thou raz'dſt not the partition-wall in vain:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh do not ſuffer't to be built again.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>On the Spring.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>MY Senſe is raviſh'd, when I ſee</l>
               <l>This happie Seaſons <hi>Jubilee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What ſhall I term it? a new birth,</l>
               <l>The reſurrection of the earth,</l>
               <l>Which hath been buried, we know,</l>
               <l>In a cold Winding-ſheet of ſnow.</l>
               <l>The Winters breath had pav'd all o'er</l>
               <l>With Cryſtal Marble th'world's great floor:</l>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170697:50"/>
               <l>But now the earth is livery'd</l>
               <l>In verdant ſuits, by <hi>April</hi> dy'd;</l>
               <l>And, in deſpight of <hi>Boreas</hi> ſpleen,</l>
               <l>Deck'd with a more accompliſh'd green.</l>
               <l>The gaudy Primroſe long ſince hath</l>
               <l>Diſclos'd her beauty by each path.</l>
               <l>The floods, as freez'd for Chariot-proof,</l>
               <l>Were planch'd o'er with a Cryſtal roof:</l>
               <l>Now in their chanels ſweetly glide,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Nyle,</hi> when they his banks divide.</l>
               <l>The trees rob'd of their leafie pride,</l>
               <l>With moſſie frize had cloath'd each ſide;</l>
               <l>Whoſe hoary beards ſeem'd to preſage</l>
               <l>To blooming youth their winters age:</l>
               <l>But now invite to come and lie</l>
               <l>Under their quilted <hi>Canopie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Blithe <hi>Damon,</hi> like a jolly man,</l>
               <l>Long ſince unto the mountains ran,</l>
               <l>Where quietly he ſits to pipe,</l>
               <l>Whereat his lambs do ſeem to skip;</l>
               <l>Then running to their dams, they tug,</l>
               <l>VVith pleaſant ſpeed, the ſwelling dug.</l>
               <l>Anon, let's to yon hawthorn ſteal,</l>
               <l>And hearken how ſweet <hi>Philomele</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Grieves not ſo much at <hi>Tereus</hi> crime,</l>
               <l>As joys to ſee the Summer's prime.</l>
               <l>How to the Spring the whiſtling Thruſh</l>
               <l>His Sonnets ſings on ev'ry buſh!</l>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:170697:51"/>
               <l>The Sun late ſquinted from the skye,</l>
               <l>And look'd on us with half an eye:</l>
               <l>But now with glad and golden chear</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phlegon</hi> mounts up our Hemiſphere.</l>
               <l>Our blood's mild, as if by ſome art</l>
               <l>W' had ſuck'd ſome new-born infant 's heart.</l>
               <l>In brief, quaint Nature ſeems here nice</l>
               <l>In type to ſhadow <hi>Paradice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lord, all things bud, and ſhall I davour</l>
               <l>Without the ſunſhine of thy favour?</l>
               <l>VVilt never prime? haſt paſs'd a doom,</l>
               <l>That ſeaſon never more ſhall bloom?</l>
               <l>Inflict not on me ſuch a dearth,</l>
               <l>A greater curſe then on the earth.</l>
               <l>If did my ſin in <hi>Tereus</hi> ſhape</l>
               <l>Act on thy <hi>Philomel</hi> a rape;</l>
               <l>My ſoul like <hi>Progne</hi> ſhall be juſt,</l>
               <l>And on his brats revenge his luſt.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Primroſe-like</hi> Repentance riſe,</l>
               <l>Dew'd by the <hi>April</hi> of mine eyes:</l>
               <l>Then will I not doubt but next thou</l>
               <l>VVilt make each grace in order blow.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170697:51"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 22.</bibl>
                  <p n="9">9 <hi>But thou art he that took me out of my mothers womb: thou waſt my hope, when I hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed yet on my mothers breſts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10 <hi>I have been left unto thee ever ſince I was born: thou art my God, even from my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>LOrd, when the <hi>Oſtrich</hi> leaves her forlorn eggs,</l>
               <l>Nor ey'd nor watch'd,</l>
               <l>They by the ſand are hatch'd:</l>
               <l>The young ſoon uſe their wing-born leggs,</l>
               <l>And for themſelves with eager ſpeed can prey:</l>
               <l>But Lord, thou foundſt me in worſe caſe then they.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Halcyon</hi> can promiſe on the flood,</l>
               <l>That South nor North</l>
               <l>Rage, till ſhe have brought forth</l>
               <l>Among the waves her ſea-born brood:</l>
               <l>But I was ſent, young far on ſea and land,</l>
               <l>But found thus good to me nor ſea nor ſand.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170697:52"/>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>I was caſt forth, like an <hi>expoſed Elf,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As ſoon as born,</l>
               <l>Moſt wretched and forlorn:</l>
               <l>Until thou took'ſt me up thy ſelf.</l>
               <l>As if my Parents knew no other debt,</l>
               <l>They ow'd their childe, but onely to beget.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Like <hi>Moſes,</hi> young, expoſed to the floods,</l>
               <l>Where I might weep</l>
               <l>To the remorſleſs deep:</l>
               <l>Left ſince, like <hi>Iſhm'el,</hi> to the woods</l>
               <l>Of this uncertain world, where I aſide</l>
               <l>Might wander, if thou hadſt not been my guide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>And as the earth (held by thy ſecret hand)</l>
               <l>Hangs in the air;</l>
               <l>There is no thred or hair</l>
               <l>Supports the ſmalleſt duſt or grain of ſand:</l>
               <l>So while ſome wonder how it is they fall,</l>
               <l>To me 't is ſtrange, <hi>Lord,</hi> how I ſtand at all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Bleſt God, that <hi>took'ſt me from my mothers womb,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My heritance</l>
               <l>Here, is not worth a glance;</l>
               <l>In length and breadth all but a Tomb:</l>
               <l>For as th' haſt wean'd me ever ſince my birth,</l>
               <l>So ſtill th'haſt wean'd me from my mother earth.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:170697:52"/>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Yet though my friends have thruſt me from my right,</l>
               <l>As from their neſt</l>
               <l>The Eagles do deveſt</l>
               <l>Theirs who can't dare the ſun by ſight:</l>
               <l>Yet this is ſtill my glory, in all things,</l>
               <l>Th' haſt born me th'row, <hi>as 't were on Eagles wings.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Wealth is no needful adjunct unto grace.</l>
               <l>If riches are</l>
               <l>The true undoubted ſtayre</l>
               <l>That lead to glory, <hi>Jacob</hi> 's caſe,</l>
               <l>In purchaſing his bleſſing, were but poor:</l>
               <l>For he liv'd mean, while <hi>Eſan</hi> ſwell'd with ſtore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>The bleſſing ſtood not in the promis'd land</l>
               <l>So much indeed,</l>
               <l>As in the promis'd Seed</l>
               <l>Bequeath'd by <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s bleſſing hand.</l>
               <l>God's right-hand-bleſſing's ſeldom clods of earth,</l>
               <l>But ſuch as fear invaſion, plagues, nor dearth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>Yet here each birth-right's not a <hi>Type</hi> of heaven,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Canaan</hi> was</l>
               <l>T' <hi>Abraham</hi> 's ſeed; but as</l>
               <l>Th' earth 's curs'd oft, as a curſe 't is giv'n:</l>
               <l>But ſeldom (for w' are oft deceiv'd in gheſſing)</l>
               <l>The <hi>Earneſt</hi> or th' <hi>Appendix</hi> of a bleſſing.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170697:53"/>
            <lg>
               <head>12.</head>
               <l>Lord, be 't all as thy wiſdom hath decreed,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>th' art my portion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I fear no ſuch extortion;</l>
               <l>I paſs by all, and bid <hi>God ſpeed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let them go view their <hi>Landskips,</hi> while that I</l>
               <l>Do with a better birth-right pleaſe mine eye.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Job 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="20">20 I have ſinned; what ſhall I do unto thee, O thou preſerver of men?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>LOrd, I have ſin'd:</hi> O weighty words! what more</l>
               <l>Could Hell, if it repentant were, deplore?</l>
               <l>It could but ſay, VVe merit thus to die:</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo do I confeſs, ev'n ſo have I.</l>
               <l>Yet though my ſins do bear an equal bulk</l>
               <l>VVith ſome of Hell's, unequal is our mulct.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, I have ſin'd;</hi> to tell how much, there wants</l>
               <l>A ſea of Ink, as many Pens as plants</l>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170697:53"/>
               <l>Grow on the teeming earth; and ſheets as large</l>
               <l>As are the heavens, to contain the Charge:</l>
               <l>As many <hi>Items</hi> to the Charge amount,</l>
               <l>VVhich none but thy <hi>Arithmetick</hi> can count.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, I have ſin'd:</hi> what ſhall I ſay? O brief</l>
               <l>Yet full expreſſion of ſin and grief!</l>
               <l>Thus humble <hi>Penitents</hi> vent much in little,</l>
               <l>VVhile <hi>Phariſees</hi> yet vent their frothy ſpittle</l>
               <l>In ſelf-applauſe. But in my grief this clauſe</l>
               <l>I'll onely vent, and then ſit down and pauſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, I have ſin'd;</hi> when not? in life and function:</l>
               <l>VVhat time or age can plead a free diſ-junction?</l>
               <l>Not childhood: for ſin ſoon outgrew that age,</l>
               <l>And prov'd a Graduate in my Pupillage:</l>
               <l>So that I juſtly may lament, that <hi>ſin</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And I were born unſeparable twin.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, I have ſin'd:</hi> Nay, ſleep, that locks my ſence,</l>
               <l>Can hardly bat that bold intruder thence:</l>
               <l>Corruption ſtill her centinel doth keep;</l>
               <l>What Lullabee can rock her watch aſleep?</l>
               <l>Poets may feign at will; but ſhe nor weighs</l>
               <l>Dull <hi>Morpheus</hi> nor his bunch of leaden keys.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, I have ſin'd:</hi> but if I once were clear,</l>
               <l>VVhen wheels about that ſame <hi>Platonick</hi> yeer?</l>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170697:54"/>
               <l>That I might hope, when my (now-tainted) duty</l>
               <l>Might innocent appear in perfect beauty.</l>
               <l>O for that <hi>Anniverſe,</hi> to ſet me free;</l>
               <l>Hence would I fetch my bleſſed <hi>Epoche.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, I have ſin'd:</hi> but were I free, where's found</l>
               <l>That happie and no leſs then holy ground?</l>
               <l>O might I know the place, there would I raiſe</l>
               <l>And dedicate a <hi>Temple</hi> to thy praiſe.</l>
               <l>But thy bleſt winde, that breathes at liſt his grace,</l>
               <l>Can breathe his <hi>Zephyres</hi> here in ev'ry place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, I have ſin'd:</hi> and for my <hi>Irritavies</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If thou ſhouldſt not vouchſafe me true <hi>Peccavies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I ſtill ſhould ſin: let others uſe their mind,</l>
               <l>My <hi>El'gies</hi> burthen ſtill ſhall be, <hi>I've ſin'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſince I can't weep for each ſin; till death,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I've ſin'd</hi> ſhould be the burthen of each breath.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170697:54"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Mark 7.</bibl>
                  <p n="21">21 <hi>For from within, out of the heart of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, fornications, murthers,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="22">22 <hi>Thefts, covetouſneſs, wickedneſs, deceit, laſciviouſneſs, an evil eye, blaſphemy, pride, fooliſhneſs.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>IF could ſome <hi>Delius</hi> with divided hands</l>
               <l>Sound the Seas depth, and on his ſouls recorder</l>
               <l>Imprint the wracks, huge rocks, and heaps of ſands,</l>
               <l>Which there lie ſcatter'd in confus'd diſorder:</l>
               <l>This could he do, by Natures's ſtrength or art,</l>
               <l>Yet none could ſound the bottom of the heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Should ſome <hi>Ship-maſter</hi> make's <hi>fore-ſplit</hi> the Probe</l>
               <l>Of Nature's ſecrets, and ſo bring to view</l>
               <l>Land to make up a perfect earthly Globe,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Drake</hi> nor <hi>Kit Columbus</hi> never knew:</l>
               <l>Yet, as in the great world, ſo in his own,</l>
               <l>He muſt confeſs there 's yet much land unknown.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170697:55"/>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>The heart's a Sea for depth, like <hi>Sodom-lake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dead, thick, &amp; groſs; in it will ſink no good:</l>
               <l>Th' hearts land 's unknown; wherein what monſters make</l>
               <l>Their hides and dens, few yet have underſtood.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The centre may be pureſt earth;</hi> yet th' heart</l>
               <l>The bodies centre's the corrupter part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Our heart-ſtrings are the cords of vanity;</l>
               <l>Their caverns are the devil 's lurking-holes;</l>
               <l>No fit <hi>Triangle</hi> for the <hi>Trinity;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>An habitation more fit for moles:</l>
               <l>Their cauls the veils of damn'd <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus is ſum'd up man 's wretched <hi>Majeſtie.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>If thus the <hi>Sun</hi> within our firmament</l>
               <l>Into a Meteor degenerate;</l>
               <l>If thus the King within our continent</l>
               <l>Let 's ſin and luſt uſurp his Royal ſtate:</l>
               <l>If thus corrupted be the bodies leaven,</l>
               <l>How ſhall we manchets be prepar'd for heaven?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whe'er Hell be in th' earth's centre,</hi> I ſuſpend;</l>
               <l>But in man 's centre 's couch'd an Hell of ſin:</l>
               <l>Nor do ſo many lines to th' centre tend,</l>
               <l>As in a wicked heart fiends make their Inne:</l>
               <l>Which yet moſt know no more, then can be found</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Arethuſa</hi> windes beneath the ground.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170697:55"/>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Lord, ſhew me in the Mirrour of thy Law</l>
               <l>The horrour of my heart by bright reflection:</l>
               <l>In that thy Glaſs, there falſhood is nor flaw:</l>
               <l>Though wickedly ſome ſcorn its true direction,</l>
               <l>And whip the <hi>Tutor</hi> for his <hi>diſcipline;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet Lord direct me by that Glaſs of thine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Oh daign my heart with graces to perfume,</l>
               <l>And th'rowly purge it from each noiſome vapor,</l>
               <l>Whoſe rank infection choaks each neighb'ring room,</l>
               <l>And ſtrives to damp my ſoul's aſpiring tapor.</l>
               <l>O make my heart-ſtrings, Lord, thy cords of love;</l>
               <l>So mine according to thy heart ſhall prove.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Pet. 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="18">18. If the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and the ſinner appear?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>IS then with fraud</l>
               <l>The way to heaven ſtraw'd?</l>
               <l>And is it granted that our race</l>
               <l>Is ſcattered with <hi>caltraps</hi> ev'ry pace?</l>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170697:56"/>
               <l>Which if but trod on, pierce us to the ankles;</l>
               <l>And more, no wound they give, but rankles:</l>
               <l>So that it ſeems a venter</l>
               <l>At all to enter.</l>
               <l>The way to heav'n's not dam'd with trifling burs,</l>
               <l>But block'd and barricado'd with demurs.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>The world's no leſs</l>
               <l>Than a vaſt wilderneſs;</l>
               <l>Whence if heav'ns guides lead us not home,</l>
               <l>Officious hell will ſeem to lend us ſome:</l>
               <l>His fiery pillar of falſe joy he grants,</l>
               <l>His cloudy one of Ignorance.</l>
               <l>But to theſe who confides</l>
               <l>To be his guides,</l>
               <l>Is ſtraightway ſwallow'd in ſome dang'rous gulf,</l>
               <l>Or prey'd by ſin, as by ſome bear or wolf.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Who look well in 't,</l>
               <l>The world's a <hi>Labyrinth;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At each whoſe Maze who ever touch'd,</l>
               <l>But found that damned <hi>Minotaur</hi> lay couch'd;</l>
               <l>Who takes each yeelding for a firm contract,</l>
               <l>And proudly will each grace exact,</l>
               <l>Till he have all deflowr'd,</l>
               <l>And all devour'd.</l>
               <l>Let not thy <hi>Theſeus</hi> Lord, be too remiſs:</l>
               <l>My ſoul, my <hi>Ariadne,</hi> ſhall be his.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170697:56"/>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Is then each path</l>
               <l>All thus ſcatter'd with wrath?</l>
               <l>We hop'd, amongſt the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> ſcorns,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> from theſe ways had fetch'd his crown of thorns;</l>
               <l>And from theſe Turn-pikes and theſe armed Rails,</l>
               <l>Had daign'd to take his Croſs and Nails;</l>
               <l>And hence had fetch'd that dart</l>
               <l>Which pierc'd his heart;</l>
               <l>And triumph'd had in conqueſt of theſe ſpoils,</l>
               <l>And purg'd his high-way of theſe ſnares and toils.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>W' are not withſtood</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By eaſie fleſh and blood;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But <hi>Satan</hi> with our weakneſs wreſtles,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Prince of th' air</hi> which in our Region neſtles:</l>
               <l>Nay we with theſe, like <hi>Gibellines and Guelves,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Do ſide and fight againſt our ſelves;</l>
               <l>Fraud's Convoy, and Deceit</l>
               <l>Th' Inne where we bait.</l>
               <l>Though Chriſt have bought us heaven, without doubt</l>
               <l>We both muſt ſue for it, and fight it out.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>No <hi>Saint</hi> nor <hi>Martyr</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can boaſt of other Charter;</l>
               <l>All at this Croſs have Inn'd, as well</l>
               <l>As <hi>Chriſt</hi> that went that way to heav'n by hell.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertue's a narrow mean betwixt two Vices;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>On each hand are deep precipices:</l>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:170697:57"/>
               <l>Let's take (if guide we lack)</l>
               <l>That bloody track</l>
               <l>Which iſſu'd from that <hi>bleſſed Roe</hi>'s five wounds,</l>
               <l>When pierc'd and purſu'd by the Jewiſh hounds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>It can't be wav'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The righteous ſcarce are ſav'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall not the wicked then be ſwallow'd</l>
               <l>Up in the mire wherein they thus have wallow'd?</l>
               <l>If trouble ever do attend on grace,</l>
               <l>Shall peace wait on a wicked caſe?</l>
               <l>If ſcarce be ſav'd the juſt,</l>
               <l>Shall pride and luſt?</l>
               <l>If thus the caſe ſtood with that <hi>verdant tree,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How ſhall the ſtubble and the chaff go free?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>In ſack and down</l>
               <l>All thoughts of hell they drown:</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo th' Hart ends the controverſie,</l>
               <l>When he, purſu'd, flies to the Hunter 's mercy.</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo the Sparrow, by the Falcon chas'd,</l>
               <l>Did to the <hi>Stoick</hi>'s boſome haſte.</l>
               <l>Each path with pleaſure's pav'd,</l>
               <l>With beauty grav'd,</l>
               <l>Until that footing fails them ere they think;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oh then how quickly into hell they ſink!</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170697:57"/>
            <head>Grief for not grieving.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 126.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="6">6 They that ſow in tears, ſhall reap in joy.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 He that now goeth on his way weeping, and beareth forth good ſeed, ſhall doubtleſs come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with joy, and bring his ſheaves with him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>IF ever any thing be heard or ſeen</l>
               <l>That might provoke or raiſe my jocund ſpleen;</l>
               <l>How could I wiſh my lungs were made of buff,</l>
               <l>For claſps to hold me till I've laugh'd enough?</l>
               <l>But godly grief cannot one tear extort;</l>
               <l>As if my ſenſes all were made for ſport.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Have I ſuſtain'd a trivial loſs? how apt</l>
               <l>My active ſenſes are for to be rapt</l>
               <l>To th' higheſt ſtrain of paſſion? I can gloſs,</l>
               <l>Heav'n never could impoſe a greater croſs.</l>
               <l>My floodgate-ſenſe can ſtand wide ope at thoſe;</l>
               <l>But godly grief's againſt the ſtream; they cloſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170697:58"/>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>If that I hear Death's univerſal doom</l>
               <l>Hath on my friend to execution come;</l>
               <l>Methinks then had I at his funeral</l>
               <l>All <hi>Argus</hi> eyes, I could ſupply them all:</l>
               <l>But when one tells me what a <hi>Lethargie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Hath ſeiz'd my ſoul, I can nor moan nor cry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>If little bigger then an <hi>atome</hi> fall</l>
               <l>Into my eye, it ſmarts, though ne'er ſo ſmall:</l>
               <l>But what's an <hi>atome</hi> to a <hi>mountain?</hi> ſuch</l>
               <l>Like ſins I bear, yet ſtart not half ſo much.</l>
               <l>Why have I not within, through conſcience,</l>
               <l>A ſenſe of pain, as outward pain of ſenſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>If that the clouds ſome foggie miſts have ſuck'd,</l>
               <l>They'll ſhow'r them back; what can their courſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct?</l>
               <l>The Moon by tides doth purg the frothy main;</l>
               <l>The poiſon'd Spring doth clear it ſelf again:</l>
               <l>Yet I'm ſin-tainted, and what motions urge me</l>
               <l>Unto repentance, that ſhould clear and purge me?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>Were I to live the old <hi>Methus'lem</hi> 's yeers</l>
               <l>A living Conduit of inceſſant tears,</l>
               <l>I could not vie a tear for ev'ry ſin;</l>
               <l>So vain and fooliſh all my youth hath bin.</l>
               <l>Yet th'earth to bear our villanies may groan;</l>
               <l>But I am dead and ſenſleſs of mine own.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170697:58"/>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>My Conſcience, Lord, though I it light eſteem,</l>
               <l>Doth with a ſecret iſſue cloſely teem:</l>
               <l>Oh let her pregnant womb be now diſcloſed,</l>
               <l>Till that diſeaſe or age have incompoſed</l>
               <l>My ſenſe. I now ſhould court it as my friend,</l>
               <l>Which then, perhaps, may prove my foe i'th'end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lord, wound me, or I die:</hi> for I, although</l>
               <l>My caſe be deadly, am not ſick enough:</l>
               <l>O let me know I'm taken in Death's jaw,</l>
               <l>Till I am quite digeſted in her maw.</l>
               <l>For if any Conſcience, like a <hi>Lethargie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Stir not till th' hour of death, I ſadly die.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Epheſ. 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="30">30 Grieve not the holy Spirit of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ye are ſealed unto the day of redemption.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>GRieve not the <hi>Spirit!</hi> can it be believ'd</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spirit</hi> can be griev'd?</l>
               <l>Thought we God, void of paſſion, could be vext.</l>
               <l>Except we ſaw this text?</l>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:170697:59"/>
               <l>When Chriſt indeed was heres in fleſh confin'd,</l>
               <l>He wept and griev'd we finde;</l>
               <l>But thought we that a <hi>Dove</hi> which hath no gall</l>
               <l>Could once be griev'd, at all?</l>
               <l>Oh I ſhould groan 't, not meaſur 't in an Ode;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sin grieves the holy Spirit of my God.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Who would reſiſt that ſacred <hi>Dove</hi> that pecks</l>
               <l>The conſcience with checks?</l>
               <l>Who would reſiſt that <hi>Dove</hi> that <hi>helps to grone</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In an accepted tone?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who would reſiſt that <hi>Dove</hi> whoſe harmleſs beak</l>
               <l>Inſtructs us how to ſpeak?</l>
               <l>Who would reſiſt that <hi>Dove</hi> whoſe in'cent feet</l>
               <l>Shew to walk as is meet?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let not this Dove back to the Ark, and grieve</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That we on earth will none of him receive.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Here let him bring his Olive-leaf and reſt,</l>
               <l>And neſtle in our breſt.</l>
               <l>O! never let us at <hi>his</hi> gracious billing</l>
               <l>Once ſhew our ſelves unwilling,</l>
               <l>Until we new <hi>begotten are, and breed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Through his eternal ſeed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O! let us never hence reſiſt this <hi>Dove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This bleſſed Bird of love.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Dove</hi> at <hi>Mahomets</hi> ear never bill'd,</l>
               <l>Though ſo he faign the <hi>Alcharon</hi> inſtill'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170697:59"/>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>Think we, becauſe ſome ſay, <hi>Doves</hi> have no gall,</l>
               <l>God's vengeance feign'd at all,</l>
               <l>That we thus with his <hi>Spirit</hi> dare to dally,</l>
               <l>As with our Friend or <hi>Ally?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Such wanton cruelty to <hi>Chriſt</hi> we dealt</l>
               <l>When he among us dwelt;</l>
               <l>Such entertainment he whiles here receiv'd,</l>
               <l>When he among us griev'd:</l>
               <l>VVe could him to no other Inne bequeath,</l>
               <l>But to his Grave; and to no Hoaſt, but Death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>But let not ſin uſurp us; but the <hi>Spirit,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His right in us inherit:</l>
               <l>And ſince <hi>he</hi> made the heart, let none abridge</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Him</hi> of that priviledge.</l>
               <l>O let not ſin be Porter ſtill, which mocks</l>
               <l>His ſweet, his Patient knocks.</l>
               <l>Delay, <hi>like that falſe Brother, cries, I go,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But means no leſs then ſo.</l>
               <l>VVho but a begger for a ſlender pittance,</l>
               <l>VVould with ſuch patience dance for an admittance?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>O let us open, leſt his wrath break through!</l>
               <l>VVe are not thunder-proof:</l>
               <l>O let us open to his calls! ſuch knocks</l>
               <l>Ev'n might awake deaf rocks:</l>
               <l>VVho might (enamour'd on his gracious gifts)</l>
               <l>Divide their flinty clifts,</l>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170697:60"/>
               <l>Leſt he appear next in a Vulture 's ſhape,</l>
               <l>T' act on our ſouls a rape:</l>
               <l>Leſt with <hi>his</hi> lightning <hi>he</hi> our bodies harrow,</l>
               <l>Incinerate our bones, and drink our marrow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Lord, I am dull; O let thy <hi>Spirit</hi> pierce</l>
               <l>Way for a quick commerce.</l>
               <l>'Tis wholeſome <hi>Phyſick,</hi> Lord, to be ſoul-ſick;</l>
               <l>Health, to be pierc'd at quick.</l>
               <l>When ere thou com'ſt, I'm either gone from home,</l>
               <l>Or thou before I come:</l>
               <l>Next, if deny'd, break th' houſe, 't is thine, and I</l>
               <l>Allow the <hi>Burglary;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And let thy <hi>holy winde,</hi> with quick inqueſt,</l>
               <l>Enter, and raiſe his Earthquakes in my breſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Then purge thy Temple; let my fleſh ev'n long:</l>
               <l>O give each pore a tongue,</l>
               <l>To cry, <hi>Come bleſſed Spirit:</hi> let each mouth</l>
               <l>Breathe, <hi>Riſe, O North, come South;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Breathe on thy Spices, breathe, leſt that thy garden,</l>
               <l>Not blow'd, or dew'd on, harden,</l>
               <l>Like to that <hi>quondam-Nurſery</hi> of thine,</l>
               <l>Once-fruitful <hi>Paleſtine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus by thy grace refreſh'd, in thy good time,</l>
               <l>It flouriſh may, like <hi>Eden</hi> in its prime.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170697:60"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſal. 63.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="4">4 For thy loving kindneſs is better then life it ſelf.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>BEtter then life it ſelf!</hi> what's life? what blindneſs</l>
               <l>Prefers his life before thy loving kindneſs?</l>
               <l>Were life poſſeſt of all that feigned bliſs</l>
               <l>The <hi>Alchoran</hi> can promiſe after <hi>this;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet what were all theſe joys? what guſt or ſavor</l>
               <l>Had all theſe pleaſures yet, without thy favor?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>Could man re-purchaſe, by ſome unknown price,</l>
               <l>His ancient Mannor, real <hi>Paradice:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Should he be re-ſaluted, The ſole Lord,</l>
               <l>And <hi>ſeiſin</hi> giv'n him by that <hi>flaming ſword:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Could Man have all theſe joys, what were 't to be</l>
               <l>At peace with Creatures, and at war with Thee?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>Should man be with that <hi>choſen veſſel</hi> rapt</l>
               <l>Up into heav'n, and there in glories wrapt:</l>
               <l>Should he with ſuch a holy violence</l>
               <l>As was <hi>Elijah</hi> once, be wafted hence:</l>
               <l>Could man have theſe, without thy love what were it</l>
               <l>To what <hi>Elijah</hi> and bleſt <hi>Paul</hi> inherit?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170697:61"/>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>If the wings of our time of life did flag</l>
               <l>Nothing below the age of crow or ſtag;</l>
               <l>If in man's body fitly did condenſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>An equal temper of the elements:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet what were life, without <hi>thine</hi> from above?</l>
               <l>Or breath, without the <hi>breathings</hi> of thy love?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Life</hi> is a <hi>noble thing,</hi> by God 't was breath'd;</l>
               <l>A jewel to man's carkanet bequeath'd,</l>
               <l>To cheriſh 't by inſtinct is all our ſtrife,</l>
               <l>All good 's included in the Name of <hi>Life</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet if thy gracious <hi>Spirit</hi> not revive,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We but dead, and onely ſeem to live.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>True, a live dog exceeds a lion dead;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But a dead dog excells a life that 's led.</l>
               <l>Without thy favour, without thy direction:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy breath</hi> in us corrupts by ſins infection.</l>
               <l>Without thy love, each creature's both our Foe,</l>
               <l>And all enjoyments turn to bitter woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Except our money with thy ſtamp be coyn'd,</l>
               <l>Except our friendſhip with thy love be joyn'd,</l>
               <l>Except thy <hi>marrow</hi> do our diſh imbelliſh,</l>
               <l>Except our wine do ſavour of thy reliſh;</l>
               <l>Our money, friendſhip, all our wine and ſood,</l>
               <l>Not currant is, not true, not ſweet, not good.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:170697:61"/>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>Dear God! without thy love all creatures may</l>
               <l>Match me; I live and am, and ſo are they:</l>
               <l>No difference, without thy quickning preſence,</l>
               <l>There is 'twixt me, and unbelieving peaſants.</l>
               <l>If here thy love bear witneſs of thy choice,</l>
               <l>I in thy loving kindneſs ſhall rejoyce.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Pet. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="10">10. But the day of the Lord ſhall come as a thief in the night, in the which the heavens ſhall paſs away, with great noiſe, and the elements ſhall melt with fervent heat; the earth alſo, and the works that are therein, ſhall be burnt up.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Seeing then, that all theſe things ſhall be diſſolved what manner of perſons ought we to be in all holy converſation and godlineſs?</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Looking for and haſting unto the coming of the day of God, wherein the heavens, being on fire ſhall be diſſolved, and the elements ſhall melt with fervent heat.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:170697:62"/>
            <lg>
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>Thus learn'd,</l>
               <l>Let 's be fore-warn'd;</l>
               <l>And thus aſtoniſh'd,</l>
               <l>In time let 's be admoniſh'd.</l>
               <l>In vain our brains we pump,</l>
               <l>To tell the terrours of that trump:</l>
               <l>Cloud-rending thunders are but ſoft,</l>
               <l>Quiet as night, and ſilent as a thought;</l>
               <l>Or as the noiſleſs <hi>muſick</hi> of the Spheres,</l>
               <l>To this ſound that ſhall deaf our ears.</l>
               <l>No vapours bellowing from the ground</l>
               <l>At all are like this ſound.</l>
               <l>And if that Trump ſhall make</l>
               <l>The dead t' awake;</l>
               <l>Where ſhall it drive</l>
               <l>Th' alive?</l>
               <l>If ſhall the ſenſleſs graves and th' earth obey,</l>
               <l>Shall we not quake and tremble worſe then they?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>I wonder,</l>
               <l>If that the Thunder</l>
               <l>Makes beaſts to flee</l>
               <l>For ſafety to ſome tree:</l>
               <l>Let 's think then with what terrour</l>
               <l>Shall that loud <hi>Trump</hi> wake ſin and errour!</l>
               <l>How do we tremble if we meet</l>
               <l>The eager flaſhes of a lightning ſheet?</l>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:170697:62"/>
               <l>How do we wiſh to quench a burning City,</l>
               <l>If poſſible, with tears of pitie?</l>
               <l>If with our fev'riſh friend we fry</l>
               <l>In hearty ſympathy;</l>
               <l>How ſhall we melt as faſt</l>
               <l>As th' heavens waſt,</l>
               <l>When I and you</l>
               <l>Shall view</l>
               <l>The heavens to diſſolve, the skies to ſwelter,</l>
               <l>And ſtars in melting elements to welter,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>We count,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Sinai</hi> 's mount,</l>
               <l>When God propounded</l>
               <l>The Law, all were confounded:</l>
               <l>God 's thunder-rhetorick</l>
               <l>With lightning flaſh'd, made Nature ſick:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sinai</hi> like ſome <hi>Veſuvius</hi> ſeem'd;</l>
               <l>Its trembling womb with conſtant earth-quakes teem'd,</l>
               <l>As if the feigned <hi>Cyclops</hi> there were under,</l>
               <l>And there did forge and frame their thunder:</l>
               <l>His Law God with ſuch terrour ſpake,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It made the juſt to quake:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How will he then impeach</l>
               <l>His ſtatutes breach!</l>
               <l>And ſin how ſtrict</l>
               <l>Convict?</l>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:170697:63"/>
               <l>Shall they not feel thoſe terrours of the Law.</l>
               <l>Which they at <hi>Sinai</hi> onely heard and ſaw?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>The torrid</l>
               <l>Zone 's not ſo horrid</l>
               <l>As ſome do feign;</l>
               <l>Nor is the dog-ſtars reign:</l>
               <l>Our wits foment more fuel</l>
               <l>Then Nature gave; they 're not ſo cruel:</l>
               <l>But who hath ſo his thoughts indulg'd,</l>
               <l>To think theſe flames leſs then they are divulg'd,</l>
               <l>May fear to be caſt from this burning frame,</l>
               <l>Into an everlaſting flame,</l>
               <l>'Mong thoſe contemners of that Prophet</l>
               <l>Who did denounce that <hi>Tophet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whereon a forc'd belief,</l>
               <l>Shame pain and grief,</l>
               <l>Shall without end</l>
               <l>Attend:</l>
               <l>Where ſighs ſhall ſerve but to blow up the flame,</l>
               <l>And tears the oil, which ſhall foment the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>And thus</l>
               <l>We now diſcuſs,</l>
               <l>The world of old</l>
               <l>By <hi>Noah</hi> was foretold;</l>
               <l>And as they at his <hi>Ark,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some at our preparations bark:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Atheiſt</hi> 's ready to ask whether</l>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170697:63"/>
               <l>Our <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Mahomet</hi> will come together;</l>
               <l>Since both have been expected long, t' inveſt</l>
               <l>Theirs in a <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of reſt.</l>
               <l>There 's none but both upbraids and pities</l>
               <l>Wretch'd <hi>Sodom</hi> and her Cities:</l>
               <l>Ev'n they were thus ſurpris'd,</l>
               <l>When unadvis'd</l>
               <l>They reck'ned not</l>
               <l>Juſt <hi>Lot.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And who knows <hi>Sodom</hi> 's fate, but counteth it</l>
               <l>Th' world 's future in a leſſer volume writ?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>But gheſs</l>
               <l>To what diſtreſs</l>
               <l>Was th' old world brought,</l>
               <l>Beyond conceit or thought,</l>
               <l>When void of Ark or Boat,</l>
               <l>They ſaw juſt <hi>Noah's Ark</hi> afloat!</l>
               <l>Gheſs one upon a rock that ſnores,</l>
               <l>While the wild Sea hath drown'd all neighb'ring ſhores.</l>
               <l>Anon awaking, caſts his frighted eyes</l>
               <l>Upon a ſhip which ſcorns his cries;</l>
               <l>Now looks each minute for ſome wave,</l>
               <l>To waft him to his grave:</l>
               <l>Such even was their fate,</l>
               <l>When they too late.</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s hoſt,</l>
               <l>Were loſt.</l>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170697:64"/>
               <l>And now what ſaving knowledge will diſſever</l>
               <l>From ſerious thoughts, that dropſie and this ſever?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>Oh how</l>
               <l>Methinks I now</l>
               <l>See that day dawn,</l>
               <l>Tombs ſplit, and graves to yawn!</l>
               <l>Methinks I hear no noiſe,</l>
               <l>But ſeems to accent forth <hi>that voice,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Some have let looſe the Torrid Zone;</l>
               <l>The skie 's one fiery element alone;</l>
               <l>Th' earths veins and minerals run in one ſtream,</l>
               <l>At th' heavens all-diſſolving beam:</l>
               <l>All waters (as thoſe that did drench</l>
               <l>Divine <hi>Elijah</hi> 's trench)</l>
               <l>The fire doth ſeem to ſup,</l>
               <l>And ſwallow up.</l>
               <l>What flames diſplay</l>
               <l>The day!</l>
               <l>Now let nor <hi>Daedalus</hi> truſt to his wing,</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Gyges</hi> walk inviſibly in 's Ring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>This wee</l>
               <l>May all foreſee:</l>
               <l>Hear we not <hi>rumours</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of war,</hi> revenge, and humours?</l>
               <l>As if we would th' earth 's fall</l>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170697:64"/>
               <l>With flames of rage and luſt foreſtal:</l>
               <l>Some ſtars are fallen, and long ſince,</l>
               <l>That they were flaſhie Meteors convince.</l>
               <l>The fixed ſtars ſeem Planets, and, God knows,</l>
               <l>Meet in conjunction but t' oppoſe:</l>
               <l>They who did pillars ſeem, and props,</l>
               <l>Prov'd <hi>Egypts</hi> reeds t' our hopes.</l>
               <l>And if theſe are not ſignes</l>
               <l>How th' world declines.</l>
               <l>I to juſt Zeal</l>
               <l>Appeal.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our Goſpels ſun in darkneſs hath been urn'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And into blood the Moon our Church been turn'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>What men</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Should we be then?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How faithful we</l>
               <l>In meaſure and degree:</l>
               <l>How watchful, wiſe, and wary,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He that comes, will come, and not tarry.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How ought we now to heav'n exhale</l>
               <l>Our timely ſighs in a repentant gale?</l>
               <l>How ought we now, againſt this day of fears,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Gods bottle</hi> fill with mourning tears?</l>
               <l>That in this day, when air nor pool</l>
               <l>Shall not refreſh nor cool;</l>
               <l>When waters ſhall not drench,</l>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170697:65"/>
               <l>And much leſs quench,</l>
               <l>Nor ought refreſh</l>
               <l>Our fleſh:</l>
               <l>We may be cheared by that <hi>North and South,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which ſhall refreſh our ſcorchings, cool our drouth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>Dread God,</l>
               <l>This <hi>Period</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cannot be far;</l>
               <l>Though thou wilt ſend no ſtar</l>
               <l>Before thee now, as when</l>
               <l>Thou didſt at firſt to thoſe <hi>Wiſe-men:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet Wiſe-men now, with eyes as ſteady,</l>
               <l>View in the eaſt thy ſtar there fix'd already.</l>
               <l>O ſend thy <hi>Spirit,</hi> by a privie Seſſion,</l>
               <l>T' arraign and ſentence each tranſgreſſion:</l>
               <l>Let 's now condemn our ſelves, that we</l>
               <l>May then b' abſolv'd by thee.</l>
               <l>O let 's now for each fault</l>
               <l>Our hearts aſſault;</l>
               <l>Our ſelves contemn,</l>
               <l>Condemn:</l>
               <l>Then ſhall that flame our joyful <hi>Bonefire</hi> be,</l>
               <l>And that <hi>Trump</hi> ſound our happie <hi>Jubilee.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170697:65"/>
            <head>On the death of that worthy ingenious GENTLEMAN, <hi>John Ayſhford</hi> Eſq; Who departed this life, <hi>May</hi> 19. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 54.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ANd art thou dead? nor can Religion raiſe</l>
               <l>Thy body as immortal as thy praiſe?</l>
               <l>Neither can quick'ning Vertue, as a ſigne</l>
               <l>Thou lov'dſt her, chuſe thy body for her ſhrine?</l>
               <l>My grief 's too dull; I 'd in a ſerious plea</l>
               <l>'Twixt Grief and Reaſon, melt into a Sea.</l>
               <l>Come, in a weeping cloud let 's mix our tears,</l>
               <l>Till they through his drop, as through <hi>Riſpah's</hi> herſe;</l>
               <l>And as <hi>Romes</hi> Emperour by a remote</l>
               <l>Kinde of exceſs, made ſhips in wine to float;</l>
               <l>Let 's make our friends cheſt ſwim in pious Brine,</l>
               <l>And riot more in tears, then he in wine.</l>
               <l>Could after-ages know thee, with what flaſhes</l>
               <l>Of love and praiſe would Wit adore thy aſhes!</l>
               <l>How would they for thy ſacred duſt explore,</l>
               <l>As greedily as ſome for golden Ore!</l>
               <l>How would they ſeek thy bones, (as ſome of old</l>
               <l>Did <hi>Scanderbeg</hi> 's) t' enamel them in gold!</l>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170697:66"/>
               <l>All in remembrance that the time was, when</l>
               <l>Thou liv'dſt the Jewel and <hi>delight of men.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Youth could not wiſh ſociety more ſweet,</l>
               <l>Nor graver age, more ſolid and diſcreet:</l>
               <l>As fervent in Religion as any,</l>
               <l>Yet knew to difference 'twixt Zeal and Zany.</l>
               <l>A Gentleman, yet learned; rich, yet free,</l>
               <l>Not out of luſt, but liberality.</l>
               <l>Poor Truth hath loſt a ſhoulder of ſupport,</l>
               <l>And innocence an arm for to retort</l>
               <l>Her injuries: the poor, the lame, the dim,</l>
               <l>Have loſt a hand, a foot, an eye in him.</l>
               <l>What can I more? w' have loſt, by this remove,</l>
               <l>A head of counſel, and a heart of love.</l>
               <l>Reader, didſt know how worth? I need not borrow</l>
               <l>Terms to perſwade thee, then, to raiſe thy ſorrow:</l>
               <l>But if thou knew'ſt him not, or liv'dſt remote,</l>
               <l>I'm ſure th' haſt cauſe to weep thou knew'ſt him not.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Sic flevit Daniel Cudmore.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170697:66"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
